<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great mysterie of God: or, The vision of the evening and the morning opened. Whereby comparing Scripture with acts of divine providence, will plainly appeare that the ruine of mysticall Babylon, and the erecting of spirituall Jerusalem are the ground of these present commotions; which are not to cease till by meanes of this present Parliament. The worke being so compleated, that Christ shall in and by his saints in tranquility reigne on earth one thousand yeares.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 217 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E276_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209877</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868728</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868728</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121084</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85605)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121084)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 46:E276[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great mysterie of God: or, The vision of the evening and the morning opened. Whereby comparing Scripture with acts of divine providence, will plainly appeare that the ruine of mysticall Babylon, and the erecting of spirituall Jerusalem are the ground of these present commotions; which are not to cease till by meanes of this present Parliament. The worke being so compleated, that Christ shall in and by his saints in tranquility reigne on earth one thousand yeares.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wright in the Old Bayley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 2d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121084:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The great MYSTERIE OF GOD: OR, The Viſion of the Evening and the Morning opened.</p>
            <p>Whereby comparing Scripture with acts of Divine Providence, will plainly appeare that the Ruine of Myſticall Babylon, and the Erecting of ſpirituall Jeruſalem are the ground of theſe preſent Commotions; which are not to ceaſe till by meanes of this preſent Parliament.</p>
            <p>The Worke being ſo compleated, That Chriſt ſhall in and by his Saints in tranquility reigne on earth one thouſand yeeres.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Revel. 1.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed is he that readeth and they that heare the words of this Propheſie, and keep thoſe things that are written therein, for the time is at hand.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exod. 15.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord ſhall reigne for ever and ever.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Dan. 2.22,</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For he revealeth deep and ſecret things, he knows what is in the dark, and the light dwelleth with him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Revel. 22.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Stale not the ſayings of the Propheſie of this Booke, for the time is at hand.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>John Wright</hi> in the old Bayl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y. 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:121084:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121084:2"/>
            <head>To the RIGHT HONOURABLE the Houſe of PEERS: AND TO THE HONOURABLE the Houſe of COMMONS Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Igh and moſt honoured ever renowned Senators, the Lord of his free grace and love having about ſome two or three yeers ſince caſt my thoughts and meditations upon that great viſion ſhewed unto his ſervants &amp; Prophets <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>John</hi> concerning the time of the raign and the ruine of theſe five grand enemies of the Church, ſet forth by the Spirit of God to <hi>Daniel</hi> to be one Image, and to <hi>John</hi> to be but one Beaſt,
<pb facs="tcp:121084:3"/>all in league together to perſecute the Saints of God, (by comparing the Words of God and the Acts of Gods providence) one with the other, I finde that theſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies deſtruction is nigh at hand, and Gods peoples finall deliverance neere; yea, the worke is begun already and will not be long before the Lord will conſummate it. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, I humbly conceive, that You are thoſe two great Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes which the Spirit of Chriſt foretold long ſince ſhould be raiſed up to Heaven the high place of Juſtice and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, though all the people and Saints of God from the yeer of Chriſt 375. unto 1639. be reckoned for his Witneſſes, and ſo looked upon by Chriſt, becauſe they all bore witneſſe unto thoſe Truths of Chriſt which that man of ſinne denied; yet You in a more eſpeciall manner at this time, becauſe You are not onely to proteſt againſt Antichriſt and his grand lie, who ſaid, That the power of Churches and States belonged to him. But You are that Judgement which ſhould ſit and take his Kingdome and Dominion from him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.26.</note> raiſed up to Heaven by the power of Chriſts Spirit for the ſame end.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34, 45.</note> And by that little ſtone cut out of the Mountaine without hands even by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God the day You aſcended up into Heaven, by this little ſtone ſhall you deſtroy all thoſe enemies; and when You have taken all powers from them,<note place="margin">As will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appeare in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. Pſal. 149.6.</note> the Civill power will remaine in Your hands as You are Chriſts civill Magiſtrates, and all the exerciſe of the Eccleſiaſticall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Churches ſhall You give unto the people of God, (which are the Body of Chriſt, whereof You being Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) and ſitting with the reſt of Your Brethren in Gods Houſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2, 10.</note> ſhall exerciſe that ſpirituall Sword; and by Your leave and Authority the Saints of God are to build that holy City new Jeruſalem,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.6.</note> where God and the Lambe will have his Throne.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.1.</note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:121084:3"/>
            <p>He who is the meaneſt and loweſt Inſtrument that ever the Lord Chriſt made uſe of for ſo great a worke, doth humbly crave leave to conceale his name, and to preſent theſe his Labours to Your Honours, that the whole world may ſee and know what great things Chriſt will by You doe for his Church and people.</p>
            <p>The Lord make good his great and gracious promiſe unto You,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.6.</note> who hath promiſed to be a Spirit of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to You that ſit in Judgement, and Strength to You that have turned the battell to the gate, and for a Crowne of glory, and for a Diadem of beauty unto the reſidue of his people.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:121084:4"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He union and oneneſſe of all the grand enemies of the Church of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.26.</note> from the evening to the morning, with their fury and rage againſt the people of the moſt High, and the time of their deſtruction and ruine, with the time of the Churches Captivity, with thoſe ſeverall Titles which the Spirit of God ſets them forth by, ſutable to their conditions they were to be in, and the time of the enemys fall, &amp; the finall deliverance of the Church, together with the ways and means of their Redemption is called <hi>The great Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7. <hi>and</hi> 5.1. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.9. <hi>and</hi> 8.19. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1. <hi>and</hi> 22.6. <hi>and</hi> 5.3.</note> written in a little booke and ſealed on the back ſide with ſeven ſeales, and the words cloſed up and ſealed till the time of the end: A myſtery and viſion ſhewed to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> and <hi>John.</hi> But no man was found in Heaven nor in Earth, neither under the earth worthy to open and to read the booke,<note place="margin">Verſ. 5.</note> neither to looke thereon; but the Lord Jeſus, the Lion of the Tribe of Judah, he prevailed and was counted worthy to open this little booke and to looſe the ſeven Seales thereof. And you have this Lion or Lambe who had been ſlain opening all the ſeven Seales <hi>5, 6, 7,</hi> and <hi>8.</hi> Chapters. And this myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God or little booke, was not finſhed or opened till the ſeven Trumpets ſounded,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.5.</note> and then an Angel that ſtood upon the ſea and upon the earth, lift up his hand to Heaven; and ſware by him that liveth for ever and ever, That there
<pb facs="tcp:121084:4"/>ſhould be time no longer, that is, that the enemies of the Church ſhould have no longer time to tyrannize and raign over the Churches of the Saints, nor the myſterie any longer concealed. And ſaith further, that in the dayes of the voyce of the ſeventh Angell (when he ſhall begin to ſound) the myſterie of God ſhould be finiſhed.<note place="margin">Verſ. 7.</note> And we ſhall finde that this Angel did not begin to ſound untill the witneſſes were aſcended up to Heaven, and the tenth part of that Antichriſtian City fell.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.5.</note> Therefore though many learned and pious men have underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to open this book and to looſe the ſeven Seales thereof,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.4.</note> yet indeed were not able (becauſe) they were not found worthy and (becauſe this viſion was to be ſhut up for many dayes) and the words and booke cloſed up and ſealed with ſeven Seales till the time of the end.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.26, <hi>and</hi> 12.19.</note> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.1.</note> Something indeed hath bin done by way of Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory and paraphraſing upon the Text:<note place="margin">Verſ. 9, 10.</note> but to open the booke and looſe the ſeven Seals did only belong to that Lamb which was in the midſt of the throne, and of the foure beaſts, and in the midſt of foure and twenty Elders; he onely was counted worthy becauſe he had beene ſlaine, and redeemed his Church and people not onely from the wrath of God and Hell, and Death, but out of every kinred, and tongue, and people, and nation, and hath made them to God Kings and Prieſts, and they ſhall reigne with Chriſt upon the earth <hi>1000.</hi> yeers.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4.</note> This myſterie being now finiſhed, and this little booke and ſeales broken open,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11, 12.</note> which were done the yeere the witneſſes aſcended up to Heaven <hi>1639</hi> when the tenth part of that Antichriſtian City fell (as ſhall be ſhewed at large in its place) then the Lord commanded his Prophet to make it plaine upon tables,<note place="margin">Verſ. 13.</note> that he may run that readeth it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.2, 3. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.10.</note> And ſaith further, that at the end the viſion ſhall ſpeake and not lye: The Lord promiſing they that are wiſe ſhall underſtand this viſion at the time of the end.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.6.</note> Now they are counted wiſe and bleſſed in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,
<pb facs="tcp:121084:5"/>to underſtand a viſion or myſtery and the interpretation thereof,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.2.</note> the words of the wiſe God and his darke ſaying; who ſearch and read the books and rolls wherein God hath wrapped and folded up theſe great myſtery of the enemys ruine and the Churches deliverance: and that trace and eye God in thoſe ſecret wayes of his providence as that holy man of God did, <hi>Pſal. 107.</hi> By which acts the Lord makes his viſion and myſtery plain upon tables, that he that runs may read. The Lord of his free love and grace having given ſome underſtanding in this great myſtery and viſion, accordingly we will by Gods aſſiſtance endeavour to hold forth this light, knowing that it is a great and hainous ſinne inexcuſable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God at that great day, either to put our light under a buſhell, or to hide that talent in the earth which the Lord hath giuen us to trade with for his glory, his Churches good, and our owne everlaſting comfort. Therefore we will declare and make knowne what we underſtand of this great myſtery in ſeverall Chapters. What is gold and pure mettall, will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the day of fiery triall; but what is hay and ſtubble ſhall be burned (which is my hearts deſire.)</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121084:5"/>
            <head>THE MYSTERY OF God opened.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Oneneſſe of thoſe five grand enemies of the Church, <hi>Daniels</hi> foure Beasts and little Horne, ſet forth by one Image and one Beaſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe foure Beaſts and little Horn that carried the Church of God captive at the firſt into <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> ſome 600. yeers before Chriſt, and hath kept them in bondage 1600. yeers, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.15.</note> all theſe were confederate together to break, devour, and trample under their feet with great fury, rage,<note place="margin">Dan. 7.7.</note> and malice all the time of their reigne,<note place="margin">Iſa. 21.15.</note> are therefore ſaid to make a Covenant with Hell and Death for the ſame purpoſe. Firſt,<note place="margin">Dan. 2.31.</note> the enemies are ſet forth by one Image, the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> being the head of it, who carried the Church of God firſt captive, <hi>ver.</hi> 38. is the firſt Beaſt, <hi>chap.</hi> 7.4. The King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> which is the Breaſt and Armes of this Image, who took the Kingdome from the King
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121084:6"/>of <hi>Babylon,</hi> Dan. 5.31. was <hi>Daniels</hi> ſecond Beaſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.5. The Belly and Thighs of this Image was the King of <hi>Graecia,</hi> who took the Kingdom from the King of <hi>Perſia, Dan.</hi> 8.6, 7. &amp; 20, 21. which was <hi>Daniels</hi> third Beaſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.6. The Legges and feet was the King of the Romans, who took the Kingdome from the Grecians, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.20. ſet forth by this Character, <hi>a raiſer of Taxes,</hi> as indeed he was, as we may ſee plainly, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.1, 2: he was <hi>Daniels</hi> fourth Beaſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.7. and was more terrible in his perſecuting the people of God then any of the three Kings or Monarchs were that went before him, ſet forth in theſe words,<note place="margin">Verſe 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Dreadfull, terrible, and ſtrong exceedingly, and had great iron teeth, who devoured and broke in pieces, and ſtomped the reſidue under his feet.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.41.</note> And in this Kings dayes, this great Kingdome and Monarchy was divided into ten Provinces or Kingdomes, ſet forth by ten hornes, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.7. and by ten toes, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.41. which were on his feet, but yet all under his power and juriſdiction, and therefore he is ſaid to have ten horns, ten Kings that had ten powers under him; and theſe ten Kings are not abſolute Kings,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12.</note> therefore are ſaid to have received no Kingdome, but reigne as petty Kings under him, and ſo receive power as Kings one houre with the Beaſt, not diſtant from him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11.</note> but one with him. Now this little horne which <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw come up amongſt thoſe ten hornes, which is that ſecond Beaſt which <hi>John</hi> ſaw come out of the earth from amongſt the common men of the earth, as indeed he did, was Antichriſt, (for he did not come or iſſue from any royall race or blood) therefore called by the Spirit of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.21. <hi>verſe</hi> 24.</note> 
                  <hi>a vile perſon, to whom they ſhall not give the honour of the Kingdome, but he ſhall come in peaceably and obtaine the Kingdome by flatteries,</hi> as you may read, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. So that the Roman Monarch, who is ſet forth by a <hi>raiſer of Taxes,</hi> was deſtroyed neither in anger nor in battell, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. but this little horne through his policy, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed craft to proſper in his hand;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.25.</note> he is noted to be very deep and ſubtill, underſtanding darke ſentences, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. ſhewing ſignes, and wonders,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marke</hi> 13.22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.13, 14.</note> and miracles, making fire to come downe from Heaven, by which ſigns he deceives the whole world, &amp; would have ſeduced the Elect, if it had been poſſible; and by his policy and craft he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to work himſelf into favour with <hi>Constantin,</hi> 320. who gave him the power of the civill ſword in <hi>Rome,</hi> and the other places adjacent in his time,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2.</note> &amp; afterward obtained the whole Kingdom or Monarch by flattery from the Dragon the Roman Emperour, and therefore he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121084:6"/>is ſaid to give him his power, ſeat, &amp; great authority:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.23.</note> for after he had made a league with the Roman Emperour about 365. he works de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully &amp; became ſtrong with a ſmall people; therfore ſaith the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, his power ſhall be mighty, but not by his own power, no,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.14.</note> for he got the power from the Roman Emperour by flattery and deceit, and not by ſtrength of Armes; neither did the Romans give him the honour of the Kingdome at the firſt, but he by his policy and craft, like a Serpent, wound himſelfe into the Roman Beaſt, and ſo became one with him; and ſo this Antichriſtian Whore made the Roman Emperour her ſtalking-horſe to carry her to the Kings of the earth, that ſhee might commit ſpirituall fornication with them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.3, 7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.3.</note> and make all the Inhabiters of the earth drunk with the wine of her ſpirituall fornication, <hi>v.</hi> 3. And this is noted in the Scripture of truth, that the Roman Beaſt, and all thoſe ten Kings under him had all one mind to enſlave themſelves to this Antichriſtian Whore,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.13.</note> and gave their power and ſtrength to her: yea, ſaith the Text, <hi>God hath put it into their hearts to fulfill his will, and to agree and give their Kingdome unto the Beaſt nutill the word of God be fulfilled, ver.</hi> 17. So yee ſee he became one with thoſe four great Beaſts or Monarchs of the whole world, all folded and united into one, ſet forth by an Image, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.31.</p>
               <p>Secondly, theſe enemies of the Church of God are ſet forth by one Beaſt; <hi>The Beaſt which thou ſaweſt, was, and is not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſhall aſcend out of the bottomleſſe pit, and they that dwell on the earth ſhall wonder, whoſe names are not written in the booke of life from the foundation of the world, when they behold the Beaſt that was, and is not, and yet is:</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">☜ </seg>
                  </label> Here is a great myſtery in the oneneſſe of theſe five great Monarchs, the Babylonian, the Perſian, the Grecian, the Roman, and laſt of all the Pope or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Monarch, all make up but one Beaſt, who was, and is, and is not. For to underſtand this aright, we muſt find out the time of this viſion, when <hi>John</hi> did ſee this Beaſt, in which of theſe Kings reigne it was: It is plaine and evident both by Scripture and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Hiſtories, that <hi>John</hi> ſaw this viſion when the Roman Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy was extant, and therefore this Beaſt (is) was, and is not. The Babylonian, the Perſian, and Grecian Monarchs was; they all had their time who were conſiderable with the other two grand enemies of the Church which followed after them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.15.</note> and had made a Covenant with hell and death to ſet themſelves againſt God and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121084:7"/>his Church. Theſe three great Beaſts were once in being, but at this time,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11</note> when <hi>John</hi> ſaw this viſion, were gone and dead. That ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Beaſt which <hi>John</hi> ſaw come out of the earth, is not, or is not yet come, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. is not and ſhall aſcend out of the bottomleſſe pit, and this is Antichriſt; he was not come at this time, for he could not come till he that did let or hinder his comming was taken out of the way,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7.</note> ſaith the Text, which was the Roman Emperour: And being one with thoſe former Beaſts that went before him, by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and confederacy with them, he is ſaid to be this Beaſt as well as they; but being not come the Spirit of God ſaith, he is not, or is not yet come, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.10.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, (yet is) the three former Beaſts was not, they were gone, the little horne Antichriſt he is not yet come, but the Roman Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch he was then extant, when <hi>John</hi> ſaw this viſion, and is ſtill in being; and that he was extant in <hi>Johns</hi> time, it's plaine and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent was the Roman Emperour,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.1.</note> for he is ſaid to have ſeven heads and ten hornes; now none of the other three Monarchs had their Kingdome divided into ten Provinces or Kingdomes, over which there was ten Kings.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.41, 42</note> But this Kingdome in his time, the Scriptures note, was divided into feet and toes, into ten Kingdome which had ten Kings, ten heads over them, reigning one houre with the Beaſt a ſhort time:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12.</note> And this Roman Beaſt had ſeven heads, he was not onely mighty ſtrong (having ten horns) but alſo full of ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and craft, ſet forth by ſeven heads; ſeven is a number of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; to note that he was perfect and compleat in pollcy, to doe hurt and miſchiefe to the Church of Chriſt: Theſe ſeven heads are ſet forth by mountaines,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.9.</note> to note their great power which the Roman Emperour had to deſtroy the Saints of God, not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his ten hornes only, but alſo his ſeven heads, full of ſubtilty &amp; craft, which were as ſo many mountaines of ſtrength, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith the Spirit of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.9.</note> 
                  <hi>here is the mind that hath wiſdome:</hi> A wiſe man knowes that wiſdome and policy is ſeated in the head, which is the proper ſeat of wiſdome, and not any naturall power of fleſh, which is ſet forth uſually by the Arme: Neither are theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven heads ſeven mountaines, on which <hi>Rome</hi> is built (as ſome have ſuppoſed) but ſeven mountaines of wiſdome and policy: All theſe ten hornes and ſeven heads or hils of policy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.8.</note> did the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour reſigne to the vile perſon, Antichriſt, who is ſaid to come up
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121084:7"/>out of the bottomleſſe pit, becauſe he was ſo deep in his ſubtity and craft: The Roman Beaſt and his ten hornes and Kings had one mind, and gave their power and Kingdome to this Antichriſtian Beaſt, and likewiſe theſe ſeven heads,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.11.</note> and therefore he is ſaid to be of the ſeven: ſo the Roman Beaſt furniſheth him with power and policy to doe as much hurt and villany to the people of God: as himſelfe did: And yet Antichriſt is ſaid to bring another head of policy and craft with him beſide theſe ſeven which the Roman Beaſt reſigned up to him: The Beaſt which was and is not (even he is the eighth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>verſe</hi> 11. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.23.</note> he bringing another head of policy with him) and therefore he is ſaid to underſtand dark ſentences, and to have poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and craft, <hi>ver.</hi> 25. and to ſhew ſuch ſignes and wonders as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Elect, if it were poſſible, and doth great wonders,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 3.22.</note> ſo that he makes, as it were,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.11.</note> fire to come downe from Heaven in the ſight of men; this eighth head of policy, the Roman Beaſt had not, but Antichriſt brings this along with him, the Beaſt that was, and is not, he is the eighth. Thus were theſe five great Beaſts made up into one Beaſt, making over their power and policy ſucceſſively one to another, to perſecute and deſtroy the Church of Chriſt, and the Saints of the moſt High,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.15.</note> by League and Covenant made with death and hell for many yeares.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> This Chapter treats of theſe two witneſſes, or opens thoſe ſeverall titles which the Spirit of God is pleaſed to ſet forth his people by in the time of their exile, ſuitable to the ſtate and condition wherein they were at the ſame time.</head>
               <p>THe people of the moſt High are ſet forth by the Spirit of God, by ſeverall titles, while they were in their great exile and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity under theſe five devouring beaſts; very ſuitable to that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition wherein they were at the ſame time. But he ſets forth the ſtate of the Church in what condition it was in Antichriſts time, eſpecially by thoſe titles he put upon them.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, he cals them his two Witneſſes. Firſt witneſſes; becauſe they did beare witneſſe againſt that grand lye of Antichriſt, who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121084:8"/>denied the Church power to be in the hands of the Spouſe of Chriſt, and that Chriſt had not left that Eccleſiaſticall power of the Church with them, but with him, &amp; that he was Chriſts Vicegerent; ſitting in the Temple of God,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4.</note> lording it over all that is called God. To this great truth of Chriſts Kingly power in his Church do they give teſtimony and beare witneſſe, denying that he or any in the world hath power to lord it over the Church and Spouſe of Chriſt in Eccleſiaſticall matters,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3.</note> for this belongs onely to God and Chriſt, and ſo they are called Chriſts Witneſſes, <hi>I will give power to my two Witneſſes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1.</note> It was Chriſt that ſpake here, this book being called the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, which God gave unto him, they who give teſtimony to any truth, though it hath been held forth by any other going before, ſuch a one is called his witneſſe; thus God is called Chriſts witneſſe, in ſaying that he was his Sonne, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.32. <hi>John</hi> is likewiſe called Chriſts witneſſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 33. the Apoſtles are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſts witneſſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.38.3.15. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. Chriſt is called the true and faithfull witneſſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. &amp; <hi>chap.</hi> 3.14. So the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God and Churches of the Saints are ſaid to be Chriſts wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in the day and yeer that Antichriſt entred into the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and denied the Kingly office of Chriſt, <hi>Anno</hi> 375.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Title</hi> 2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.4.</note> they are called two Candleſticks, and two Olive trees: they are ſet forth by two Candleſticks and two Olive trees, to ſhew to us that at this time they were in a true Church-ſtate, as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Jewes formerly were,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20.</note> who are ſet forth by one Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, and the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> by ſeven Candleſticks, and the Officers of the Churches are ſet forth by two Olive trees, that ſtand before God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.12.</note> and are on both ſides of the Candleſtick, to empty the golden Oyle of divine truth out of themſelves into the bowle of the Candleſtick into the boſome of the Church; ſo it is clear they were at this time in a true Church ſtate,<note place="margin">Why the people of God are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led two Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks. <hi>Dan.</hi> 18.32.</note> being compleat with their Officers two Olive trees, &amp; they are called but two Candeſticks, not only to note to us that the people of God were worſhiping him aright in a Church way; but at this time when Antichriſt entred into the Temple &amp; denied Chriſts Kingly office, were few in number, even two, the leaſt of all numbers; for many profeſſors at this time did do wickedly againſt the Covenant, even broke that Church Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which was amongſt them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Title <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> they are ſet forth by this title, <hi>The Saints of the moſt high,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:121084:8"/>or high Saints;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6.14.</note> Antichriſt having entred into the Temple and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned the Lord Chriſt, and pluckt the Crowne from his head, ſtripped the Spouſe of Chriſt of her vaile, &amp; perſecuted the Church into the Wilderneſſe of that Antichriſtian world, and taken away all their Church power which the Lord Jeſus gave them in the day of their eſpouſall:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.7.</note> And therefore he is ſaid to ſcatter the power of the holy people, having ſo broken them to pieces by his hot perſecution in the yeere 375. that they could not, neither might be ſuffered to hold forth the true worſhip of God in a Church way, therefore are called Saints of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.18.21. 25, 26. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.7.</note> and high Saints, they being ſcattered ſome into one place ſome into another.</p>
               <p>The fourth title by which the people of God are ſet forth by,<note place="margin">Title <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> is a woman cloathed with the Sun, and travelling,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1, 1, 5.</note> and pained to be delivered of a man childe that was to rule all Nations with a rod of Iron; the Saints of God being broken to peeces by a wicked and unjuſt Magiſtrate, and ſcattered up and downe in the wilderneſſe, ſome here and ſome there, not being ſuffered to congregate into a true viſible Church by that man of ſinne, for the ſpace of 1260. yeares; they having been perſecuted by him that full ſpace of time, and afterwards ſlaine and laid dead for three propheticall daies and a halfe. And ſome of their brethren and fellow-witneſſes being raiſed up to the high place of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Magiſtracy, as was evident in the foregoing chapter, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.12. The reſt of the godly were now with child with this great truth of Chriſt in point of <hi>Civill Government,</hi> by which the Lord Jeſus in and by his Saints, was to rule all nations with a rod of Iron. Therefore cryed they earneſtly to God by zealous and fervent Prayer, (and to his witneſſes, their fellow-ſervants that ſate in Heaven, by humble requeſt and petition) that they might have a godly Magiſtracie ſet up in the world, and that Antichriſt that wicked oppreſſour, who had made the world as a wilderneſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.17.</note> and deſtroyed the Cities thereof, and that wicked murderer which had devoured the people of God for many ages, and ſlaine his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7, 8.</note> and laide their dead bodies in the ſtreets, might be caſt now out of heaven; the place of Judicature; and the people of God, and thoſe that would raigne for that man childe Jeſus, might be left in Heaven, to ſit as Kings in the <hi>Civill Throne.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">This birth and travell of the people of God was in the yeare 1641. and 1641.</note> And thus the Church and people of God travelled for, and tooke great pains to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121084:9"/>have it come to paſſe, and was much pained and travelled in their minds untill they had accompliſhed their deſires, and was deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of this man child, the year of Chriſt 1641. as ſhall be ſhewed more fully when we come to ſpeake of thoſe effects and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences which followed upon the witneſſes aſcending up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Thus you ſee the Spirit of God ſet forth the ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in which his Church and people were to be in the time of their exile &amp; captivity, under thoſe five grand enemies of his Saints, eſpecially that little horne Antichriſt; by theſe ſeverall titles which he gave them, very fitting and agreeable with the preſent conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they were in at the ſame time; not at any time mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome of his people, and leaving out others; but intending all of them: For Antichriſt could not deceive any of Gods Elect, it was not poſſible he ſhould.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.22. From the yeare of Chriſt 375. to 1635.</note> Therefore all of them, as one man, did witneſſe to that truth of Chriſt in point of power, that he was to ſit Lord and King in his Temple, and not Antichriſt; and to be Lord over the conſciences of his Saints and Spouſe, and not man: So they were all ſcattered into the Wilderneſſe, and there did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy and ſpeak one to another for their mutuall edification, and ſo are called Saints of the moſt High; and all of them were with childe, and travelled for a godly Magiſtracy, 1641. Therefore ſet forth by a woman in travell. So by two witneſſes yee ſee is meant all the people of God, and not two diſtinct men, or diſtinct offices, the Magiſtracy and the Miniſtery, as ſome of our learned have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, nor the two Teſtaments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III</hi> This Chapter ſhewes the time of thoſe five Monarchs raigning and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing it over the Church, (eſpecially of the little borne Antichriſt) when he began and when he ended his raigne, at the ſame time the witneſſes began to prophecy and ended.</head>
               <p>THoſe five cruell and malicious Enemies of the Church of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.26.</note> were to continue for many daies. From the very firſt beginning to the laſt period and time of their end when they ſhall be quite deſtroyed, and the Church ſet free from all her enemies,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121084:9"/>and ſet downe in peace and tranquility upon the throne with Chriſt here on Earth, to rule the Nations with a rod of Iron. The Spirit of God holds forth in <hi>Daniel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.14.</note> to be two thouſand and three hundred Propheticall daies, or naturall yeares. Six hundred years from the firſt time that the people of God, and Church of the <hi>Jewes.</hi> was carried captive by the <hi>Babylonians</hi> to Chriſts time. And from Chriſts time, to the enemies laſt period or totall ruine, and the Churches finall deliverance, 1700. yeares.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.19.</note> And then the Beaſt and Antichriſt ſhall be quite caſt out of the World, as an abominable branch. And this the Spirit of God notes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dau.</hi> 8.26.</note> that the time of this viſion is not only true, but is the viſion of the evening and morning. The evening beginning at the firſt time that the people of God went into captivity, and entred upon the night of their exile and baniſhment by the <hi>Caldeans.</hi> And the morning beginning not before all the darkneſſe of that antichriſtian night be gone, &amp; the Church freed from all her enemies,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.27. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.23.</note> and riſen with that Sun of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the thrones of his glory, to rule the Nations with a rod of Iron; <hi>And to raigne upon Mount Zion and in his new Jeruſalem, before his Antients gloriouſly.</hi> From the evening to the morning ſhall be 2300. propheticall daies, and not naturall daies, for that cannot be meant, providence hath declared the contrary very evidently.</p>
               <p>This is the full time of all the enemies raigne in generall, and of the people of Gods captivity and bondage from the evening to the morning; (but Antichriſt, that little horne or power which <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> ſaw come up amongſt the other ten hornes;<note place="margin">☜ <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.8.</note> the Spirit of God ſpake more diſtinctly and exactly of the time of his raigne, and of the time of his ruine, then of any of the other foure Monarchs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.7. and 11.12.</note> he being the laſt &amp; more cruell in his perſecution againſt the Saints, then any of the other; though the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarch came very neer to him: the time of his raigne is ſet down to be a Time, Times, and halfe a Time by <hi>Daniel,</hi> and 42. Moneths by <hi>John,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☜ <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.5.</note>) <hi>Power was given to him to continue forty and two moneths.</hi> And the Saints captivity under him the ſame time, who are ſet forth by the worke which they did, and the ſtate they were in the ſame time Antichriſt is ſaid to begin his raigne; their worke was to give teſtimony, and to beare witneſſe of that great truth of Chriſts Kingly power in his Church and Temple, and to proteſt againſt Antichriſt his lye, (who ſaid, he had the power given to him) and againſt his act, ſitting in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121084:10"/>the Temple of God. And they were to continue witneſſing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying the ſame time which Antichriſt is to raigne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6.</note> ſet forth by 1260. daies, and to be in their exile and baniſhment in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that antichriſtian world, nouriſhed and fed by Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding and overſhadowing hand of providence,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.14.</note> for a Time, Times, and half a Time, the ſame with Antichriſt. A time may be taken for 1000. yeares, times for 200. yeares, halfe a time for halfe a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years: Or thus, a time to be one year, times to be two years, halfe a time halfe a yeare; there being 1260. daies in three yeares and a half. And ſo the Holy Ghoſt reckons a day for a yeare, us he doth in <hi>Daniel</hi> in the viſion of the evening and morning,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.14, 26.</note> 2300. daies for ſo many yeares;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3.12, 6.</note> and this agrees with the other times that the witneſſes ſhould propheſie, and that the woman was to be fed in the wilderneſſe, which was 1260. daies, a daie for a yeare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many propheticall daies or naturall yeares.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.5.</note> Antichriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing forty and two moneths, being the ſame with the former, every moneth containing 30. daies, which according to the <hi>Grecian</hi> account amounts to the ſame number 1260. daies, a day for a year. So the time of Antichriſts raigne, and the people of Gods bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and ſlavery under him, is 1260. propheticall daies or naturall yeares. Now we are to finde out when he began his raigne, and when he is ſaid to end. About the yeare 320. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſtood up, the Church and people of God having been exceedingly broken to peeces, devoured &amp; trampled under foot, for ſome 320. years by <hi>Daniels</hi> fourth Beaſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtuntine</hi> ſtanding up for the Chriſtians, and favouring their way,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Syluſter</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome. Dan.</hi> 11.23.</note> thereupon reſigne the civill power of <hi>Rome</hi> and other places adjacent to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome;</hi> and ſo he began to take the power of the Emperour and the civill ſword, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing noted by <hi>Daniel,</hi> that he began by a ſmall people, and is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a little horne; as indeed they were but very few Chriſtians to the whole body of that <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, neither had he any great power at this preſent time: But at this time he did not begin his raigne, (ſome ſay) 315. or 316. but that cannot be. But moſt agree upon 365. and that the whole power of the Empire was reſigned up to him by the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour at this time, which is very like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he by his policy and craft gained the power of the Empire, at or about this time,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dau.</hi> 11.21.23.</note> or the moſt part of it; for he crept in by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little into the hearts of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, and ſo into
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121084:10"/>the hearts of his Kingdome even by flattery, and began with a ſmall people;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.25.</note> and through his ſubtilty and policie cauſed craft to proſper in his hand, and by peace deſtroyed many, pretending to the Chriſtian Emperours that he was for the good and welfare both of their ſouls and bodies, Church and Empire, and if the power of the Empire might be reſigned up to him he would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it for the good of both. Whereupon the Roman Emperour reſigned up the whole power, or moſt of it, to the Biſhop of Rome 365. or thereabout. And this is noted in the Scripture of truth. That he took away the Jewa ſacrifice the ſame yeer, called,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 9, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>The daily Sacrifice;</hi> therefore it is ſaid that an hoſt was given him againſt the daily ſacrifice, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.12. The Spirit of God chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctariſeth him by a little horne, which none of the other Monarchs were ever ſet forth by; and becauſe he is ſaid to wax great to the hoſt of Heaven, which none of the other did,<note place="margin">Verſ. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>And by him</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>was the daily ſacrifice taken away, and an hoſt was given him</hi> by the Roman Emperour <hi>againſt the daily ſacrifice;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.31.</note> 
                  <hi>and armes ſhall ſtand on his ſide, and they ſhall pollute the Sanctuary of ſtrength, and ſhall take away the daily ſeerifice, and they ſhall ſet up the abomination that maketh deſolate.</hi> Antichriſt the Biſhop of Rome could not be againſt the Jews way of worſhip,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7.</note> ſo as to deſtroy it and take it out of the way, nor pollute Gods Houſe and Sanctuary and ſet up his abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, untill the Roman Emperour was taken out of the way; that is, untill he had reſigned the civill power of the Empire to him, or moſt of it. And therefore it is ſaid, that an hoſt was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him againſt the daily ſacrifice, and armies ſhall ſtand on his part. So it's cleare, the daily ſacrifice was taken away by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and thoſe armies and hoſts were given him by the Roman Emperour; and this he did by an hoſt and by the power of aims (which was the civill power of the Empire:) and he tooke the daily ſacrifice away about 365. as <hi>Carion</hi> affirms.<note place="margin">Carian Chron. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>But the Spirit of God doth not begin his time when Antichriſt took the power of the Empire into his hand, nor when he tooke away the Jews daily ſacrifice; for if he had not entred into the Chriſtians Churches and true Temple of God, and diſ-throned Chriſt, and ſtripped his Spouſe of her vale, and ſcattered the power of the holy people by the civill ſword of the Empire, but ruled for God and Chriſt and the welfare of his people, the Spirit
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121084:11"/>of God would not have looked upon him as Antichriſt. And therefore the Lord begins Antichriſts time when he firſt entred into his Temple,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 24.</note> and ſat as God himſelfe, lording it over the conſciences of men in matters divine, which only belong to God and to Chriſt. From this time doth the Spirit of God begin An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts reigne and the Churches ſlavery and bondage under him, which he did not doe ſo ſoon as he entred upon any of the power of the Empire, either 320. or 365. for this is noted of him, <hi>He came in</hi> (ſaith <hi>John</hi>) <hi>like a Lambe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11.</note> ſeeming to all the Churches of the Saints (and to the people of the whole Empire, to be an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Lamb) one that would doe no harme, which he did not from 320. when he had the civill power of Rome and other places ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent reſigned up to him, untill he had through his policy and craft made a League with the Roman Emperour <hi>Anno</hi> 365. or thereabouts.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ban.</hi> 11.23.</note> Then after this the Spirit of God notes <hi>that he ſhall worke deceitfully;</hi> as indeed he did now at the comming in of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> that great perſecution for 320. yeers againſt the Churches ceaſed, and the Saints had through <hi>Conſtantines</hi> becomming a Chriſtian reſpite and reviving, for now the Roman Beaſt had ſuch a wound given him at this time, as if that he would die preſently and not live again. But after ſome few yeers this wound was cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and Antichriſt ſtarts up in the former Beaſts ſtead,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.8, 20.</note> and ſpeaks (like a Dragon) very great things againſt the people of God, and wrought deceitfully againſt the Saints, pretending at the firſt to be all for them, but now having got the civill power in his hand, is quite againſt them; and by this civill horne or power enters into the Temple where the people of God was congregated according to the order of the Goſpell and takes away their power, and ſo is ſaid to be a Lambe that had two horns, two powers, the Civill and Eccleſiaſticall;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eev.</hi> 13.11.</note> which was done about the yeere of Chriſt 375. ſome ten yeers after the daily ſacrifice was taken away. From this time doth the Lord reckon,<note place="margin">Antichriſt begins his reigne.</note> and thus Antichriſt is ſaid to begin his reigne 375. and reigns 1260. yeers, and the two witneſſes to be in ſackcloth, and to propheſie the full ſpace of time 1260. yeeres. Then they are to end in the yeere 1635. for 375. and 1260. makes 1635. untill this time is Antichriſt to reigne and the witneſſes to propheſie. That he began <hi>Anno</hi> 375. will appeare more fully when we come to ſpeak of the witneſſes ariſing and aſcending up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121084:11"/>and Antichriſt his fall; God having promiſed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>That at the end the viſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on ſhall ſpeake and not lie:</hi> Now it muſt ſpeake by thoſe great acts of Gods providence by which God is pleaſed to open viſions and myſteries. For this time of Antichriſts reigning over the Saints was hid from all men both in Heaven and Earth, he not beginning when he tooke the Civill power, as all our former wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have ſuppoſed, none looking to the time when he entred into the Temple, and made war with the Saints which were in a Church way, and this he tooke but by parcels. And in that he is ſaid not to begin untill he enter into the Temple, and when he entred is not recorded in Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory, truly (as I conceive) the reaſon may be, That it might be hid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The tyranny and cruelty of Antichriſt againſt the people of God all his time he was to continue, and the Saints to propheſie; and likewiſe when they had ended their teſtimony with the worke and imployment of the Saints and witneſſes while they were in ſackcloth.</head>
               <p>THe tyranny of Antichriſt is ſet forth by this, that he exerciſed all the power of the former Beaſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.3, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>the former Beaſt having given him his ſeat, power, and great authority:</hi> This Antichriſtian Whore now rides upon the Roman Emperour, and makes him her ſtalk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beaſt,<note place="margin">Verſ. 2.</note> not onely to commit ſpirituall fornication with the Kings of the earth, and make all the Inhabiters of the earth drunk with the wine of her fornication, but likewiſe to devour, breake in pieces, and ſtamp the reſidue under his feet, even the poore Saints and Churches of Chriſt for 1260. yeeres; and he is ſaid to exerciſe all the power of the former Beaſt, the Roman Emperour <hi>Daniels</hi> fourth Beaſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.14, 15 Firſt ſteps of Antichriſt, cruelty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Saints. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.38. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.30. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.32. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.28.</note> who did the ſame to the Saints as ye may ſee, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.7. And fitly called the Image of the Roman Beaſt, both in his malice, cruelty, and ſtrength. Firſt, he breaks the Saints or Churches of Chriſt in pieces the day he entred into the Temple 375. and broke that League and Church-covenant which were amongſt them, and ſo he and many more that were of them in the ſame League and Covenant, <hi>are ſaid to doe wickedly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Covenant, and his heart is ſaid to be againſt the holy Covenant;</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:121084:12"/>meaning that Church Covenant that was amongſt the people of God, for he knew very well, that ſo long as the people of God kept cloſe to that Church Covenant, that they would retaine that Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall and Church power amongſt themſelves, and ſo have kept him from mixing his cup and his inventions with the pure doctrine of the Church, <hi>therefore his heart was ſaid to be againſt this h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Covenant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.13, 14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and he brake it all to pieces, perſecuting the Saints into the Wilderneſſe,</hi> ſcattering their power up and downe into the world; here one Saint, there another, and thereupon he takes all the Church power into his hand: Thus the Church and Church Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant was broken all to pieces by him,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3, 8.</note> and ſo he ſcattered the Eccleſiaſticall Church power; for which act of his, he is called <hi>That man of ſinne,</hi> and <hi>That wicked one:</hi> and ſaith the Spirit of God, <hi>He is Antichriſt that denieth the Father and the Sonne.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.22.</note> Antichriſt he ſits in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelfe to be God, in that wicked act of his, in exalting or lording himſelfe over the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of all thoſe that are Gods, and ſo deny Chriſt to have any power in his Temple, in that he denied the Saints of it, to whom Chriſt had given it, ſaying, that he was Chriſt, that he hath power over mens conſciences in matters of worſhip, therefore ſaith our Saviour,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 21.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Falſe Chriſts ſhall come in my name,</hi> in my power, ſaying, that the power belongeth to him, and ſo he denies the Sonne;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.23.</note> now ſaith the Scripture, <hi>He that denies the Sonne, denies the Father,</hi> for he denies that God or Chriſt hath now the power in their hands, but hath delivered over to him all concerning wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in his Church,<note place="margin">verſe 22.</note> and ſo he indeed is Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>This ſinne of his is called <hi>The Mystery of Iniquity:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7.</note> It is ſuch a deep and covered ſinne as that it is called a Myſtery, having ſuch faire pretences and gloſſes going along with it; yea, and it may be he did really intend to rule for God and the good of his Church, as out of doubt it was thus with the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> at this time, 375. Therefore men might think, ſurely God and Chriſt had given him power ſo to order things both in the State and Church, that there might be a uniformity in Religion, that men might be all of one mind in the worſhip and ſervice of God, and ſo both the Church and the whole Empire might live and be in much peace and quietneſſe. Who would think this to be an evill or ſinne? If a ſinne, yet not ſuch a ſinne as the Scriptures
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121084:12"/>make it to be, no, indeed a man would not think it to be ſo at the firſt view; therefore the Spirit of God ſaith,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7.17.8. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.25.</note> 
                  <hi>That he aſcended out of the bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>omleſſe pit, digged deep for this his ſubtilty and craft, and that his working is after the manner of Satan, with all deceivableneſſe of unrighteouſneſſe, transforming himſelfe into an Angell of light through his craft and policy:</hi> pretending it is for their good and welfare, as the Serpent did to <hi>Eve,</hi> thereby deceiving the whole world,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Marke</hi> 13.22. <hi>John</hi> 10.6.8.</note> and would have done the like to the Elect of God and witneſſes of Chriſt if it had been poſſible. But the Sheep would not heare him, for they know not the voyce of a ſtranger, but they know the voyce of Chriſt and will follow him, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. But Antichriſt that was a ſtranger they would not follow, for they know not his voyce (to come from God.) Whereupon he brake them all to pieces, and their Church Covenant, and caſt the Spouſe of Chriſt out of Gods Houſe and Temple, ſitting as God himſelfe over mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, directing and teaching them how to worſhip God after his owne precepts: for which God cals him <hi>proud Lucifer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13.14.13.</note> who ſaid in his heart, I will aſcend up to Heaven, I will exalt my Throne above the Starres of God, I will be like the moſt High,<note place="margin">verſe 14.</note> (Oh proud <hi>Lucifer,</hi> ſonne of the morning:) Therefore the Lord cals him, that man of ſinne, and that wicked one and his ſinne,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.8.</note> a Myſtery. We doe not meet with the like expreſſions in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo high and ſublime, to note and ſet forth to us the heinouſneſſe of this ſinne: a ſinne next to the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, and the depth of his ſinne a Myſtery. For to take the Crown from the Kings head, and to take him off from his princely Throne, and throw him out of his Palace againſt law and juſtice, is a horrible thing yea further, to force his Queen, &amp; to make her to proſtrate her ſelfe to a ſtranger, yea, to a vile perſon, this is a ſin unparaleld; but to doe ſo to the <hi>Prince of Princes, and of the Kings of the earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5.</note> and to his Spouſe the Church of Chriſt, and Saints of the moſt High, this is a ſinne brought out of the bottomleſſe pit by <hi>Lucifer</hi> ſonne of the morning, even that ſonne of perdition, (the Lord of his free grace and mercy kept his Witneſſes from this ſinne, who now are aſcended up to Heaven to execute judgement upon Antichriſt for this ſinne.) Yea, he hath ſecretly hinted to us in holy writ, that he will keep them from this ſinne, yea, they ſhall be ſo farre from this ſinne, that they ſhall give ſome liberty to weak conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121084:13"/>for the preſent,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.11.</note> while they are pouring forth the fifth and ſixth Viall.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Antichriſt did not onely breake the Church and people of God, and that Church Covenant into pieces, but devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red many of the Saints all the time of his reigne, witneſſe all thoſe holy and godly Martyrs that ſuffered Martyrdome before and in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the reſt that were left of the Saints he ſtamped under his feet, that is, he kept them in ſlavery and bondage all his reigne, by thoſe ten hornes or Kings who gave their power and ſtrength up to him, who are ſet forth by thoſe ten toes that are on his feet.</p>
               <p>Thus Antichriſt exerciſed all the power of the former Roman Beaſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.12.</note> and exerciſed as much malice and cruelty againſt the Saints in breaking them to pieces, devouring and trampling thoſe that were left,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.7.</note> as the Roman Emperour did.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But it will be objected; how comes it to paſſe that that ſinne of Antichriſt in breaking the Churches and Church Covenant to pieces to be ſo great in him, and not in the Roman Emperour, when he did the ſame thing, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Roman Emperour did it ignorantly, Antichriſt knowingly, againſt the light of his owne underſtanding, he did it as an open profeſſed enemy; Antichriſt as a ſecret enemy and open profeſſed friend, like <hi>Judas;</hi> yea, he and the reſt with him who dealt wickedly againſt the Covenant, profeſſed themſelves to be the Spouſe and Witneſſe of Chriſt: And for them to deale treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, and break this holy Covenant and Oath of wedlock, and play the harlot, and commit ſpirituall fornications with the Kings of the earth; and not ſo onely, but to break this Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and his deare Spouſe, and take the Crowne from his head, and his Spouſe out of his boſome, and caſt him and them out of his Houſe and Temple, and ſit as Lord and King, as though he was God or Chriſt himſelfe; ſurely this is a greater ſinne then that of the Roman Emperour, for he never did ſit in the Temple ſhewing himſelfe to be God.</p>
               <p>The worke and imployment of the Saints of God, and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Chriſt, all the time of Antichriſts tyranny, and their being in ſack-cloth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3, 7.</note> was to propheſie and give teſtimony. To propheſie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121084:13"/>is to ſpeake and preach to the mutuall edification and comfort of another; this they had liberty to do all,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Car.</hi> 14.31.</note> all the time of their bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, 1260. years, <hi>I will give power to my two witneſſes and they ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3.</note> When God gives liberty and power, neither Devils nor the <hi>Roman</hi> Beaſt, or his Image the Pope can hinder them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they are to give teſtimony, or beare witneſſe to all the truths of Chriſt, eſpecially that truth which Antichriſt was to deny in point of power; that Chriſt was Lord and King over his Church; which they did from the firſt riſing of Antichriſt. 375. to his end, 1635. for they are ſaid,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7.</note> not to finiſh their teſtimony untill that time, and to his Prieſtly office; that we are freely juſtified by his grace, and not by our owne merits.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The witneſſes are ſlaine by Autichriſt, and lye dead three daies and a halfe, are raiſed upon their feet, and aſcend up to Heaven.</head>
               <p>THe witneſſes were to propheſie and give teſtimony 1260. years, from 375. to 1635. and had power given them of Chriſt ſo to do: when they have finiſhed their teſtimony and done their work,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7.</note> then Antichriſt, that Beaſt that aſcended out of the bottomleſſe pit, was to make war againſt them and ſlay them.</p>
               <p>There is a naturall, civill and ſpirituall ſlaying, we cannot ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to be meant of a naturall ſlaying: for by thoſe two witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, is meant all the Saints and people of God; and Chriſt will not ſuffer the Devill and wicked men to ſlay all his people at one time, or in one age, no not in the hotteſt perſecution of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperour, in thoſe 300. yeares, though many hundred have been ſlaine at a time. And if we ſhould underſtand by theſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes the godly ones of the Magiſtracy and Miniſtery, and to be naturally ſlaine, ſo they have been in former ages, in the daies of their propheſie, as other of the Saints have been, (as is ſet forth by the word <hi>devoure,</hi>) and ſo the Spirit of God hath ſaid no new thing, but what he had formerly ſpoken; therefore it cannot be meant a naturall ſlaying.</p>
               <p>Secondly, there is a ſpirituall ſlaying, and this cannot be meant;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121084:14"/>neither men nor Devils can ſpiritually ſlay the Saints and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Chriſt, none is able to pluck them out of Chriſts hand.</p>
               <p>There is a civill ſlaying, and that muſt needs be meant in this place. Now by civill ſlaying is meant nothing elſe but a taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all their civill power which they had, as they were free born ſubjects in the State or Kingdom wherein they live, that they might not give teſtimony to the truths of Chriſt, and propheſie to the mutuall edification and comfort one of another, as they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly done for 1260. yeares. But if any Magiſtrate or Miniſter, or private man, did proteſt againſt that grand lye of Antichriſt, ſaying that they had no Power, Pope, Cardinall, or Prelate, to ſit in Chriſts Temple, and to Lord it over the conſciences of his people, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they were caſt out of office, their mouthes were ſtopped, and their bodies impriſoned or they baniſhed out of their own native Country. And this was very apparent here in our Iſland, when moſt of the witneſſes were ſo dealt withall, who did openly oppoſe Antichriſt, between the yeare 1635. and 1638. and a halfe: Thoſe three ever honoured worthies of Chriſt, Maſter <hi>Burton,</hi> Doctor <hi>Baſtwick,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Pryn,</hi> (who were a lively embleme of the reſt, witneſſing againſt the power of the Prelates,) and others, who were forced to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lye their owne Country.</p>
               <p>Thus were they civilly ſlaine by Antichriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. and 11.</note> and their dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies lay in the ſtreets of that ſpirituall <hi>Sodome,</hi> three daies and a halfe, the power being taken out of their hands that they might neither give teſtimony nor propheſie; in the Scripture ſenſe they are ſaid to be not only ſlaine, but to lye as dead bodies; that is, men made as uſeleſſe in the world: And [they would not ſuffer their dead bodies to be put in graves.] That is, they would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer humane courteſies to be ſhewed to them, not to buy nor ſell, no not not to have commerce or converſe with any;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev</hi> 13.17.</note> ſo bitter and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el were the Pope and Prelates between 1635. and 1638. and a half. We in <hi>England</hi> found it by wofull and ſad experience, and our neighbour Nation of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in both which moſt of Chriſts wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes were ſlaine.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.2.</note> Inde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed there were other witneſſes which the Lord Chriſt had in other places, but thoſe had got victory over the Beaſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.14, 15.</note> and his Image, and marke, and number of his name, <hi>who came out of the great tribulations,</hi> had indured great conflicts with Antichriſt, but at laſt came out of them, and ſo made their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121084:14"/>garments white with the blood of the Lambe, and now worſhip God and Chriſt in his houſe and Temple day and night,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.4.</note> who are the ſealed ones of God; ſealed, when the ſixth Viall was to be poured upon the great River <hi>Euphrates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.12.</note> when thoſe foure Angels were looſed that were bound in that River. Theſe were not ſlaine by Antichriſt, but are ſaid to be upon Mount <hi>Sion</hi> with the Lambe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.14.</note> upon the hill of his Church, ſinging a new Song,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1.</note> which none can ſinge but the 144000. who have not defiled themſelves with that Antichriſtian Whore, or any of her ſpirituall fornications,<note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note> theſe are redeemed from amongſt men, from being ſlaine by Antichriſt,<note place="margin">Verſ. 4.</note> that they might be the firſt fruits to God and to the Lambe in a Church way.</p>
               <p>When Antichriſt had thus ſlaine the witneſſes, and laid them dead three daies and a halfe, not ſuffering their dead bodies to be put in graves; then at the end of time, which was 1638. and a halfe, juſt at that inſtant of time did the Spirit of God enter into the hearts and ſpirits of the godly part,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.11. <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.1.</note> both in <hi>England</hi> and in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as he did into <hi>Cyrus.</hi> And they ſtood upon their feet] that is, they tooke courage, and put liberty, life, goods, and all to their hands, and tooke to them all that power and ſtrength they had to free themſelves from that dead and ſlaviſh condition where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Antichriſt had brought them. Thus the Spirit of life from God entred into them, and they ſtood upon their feet; and ſaith the Text, <hi>Feare fell upon them that ſaw them.</hi> And indeed ſo there did fall a great fear upon all that ſaw them of the antichriſtian party,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.11.</note> both in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> yea, at <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, witneſſe the Popes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterpeece. All that knew of the godly party riſing, feare and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ſeized upon them, and when they ſtood thus upon their feet,<note place="margin">Verſ. 12.</note> ready to do any ſervice that God ſhould put them upon, <hi>Preſently they heard a voyce from Heaven ſaying, Come up hither.</hi> This voice was not from the materiall Heavens, or the third or high Heavens, where God and his Angels are, for then they ſhould have aſcended up thither: neither is this voice from the Church or Temple, for then they ſhould at the ſame time have aſcended up into a true Church-State; and if they had done ſo, Antichriſt would quickly have brought them down, &amp; broken them all to peeces again, as he had formerly done by the power of the civill ſword, which was ſtill in his hand. Therefore by Heaven is meant in this place, the place
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121084:15"/>of Judicature, the mount of the Congregation,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>ſſa</hi> 14.13.</note> the place of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the voice came from this Heaven. That wiſe and godly men would now aſcend to this place to do juſtice upon Antichriſt, who had ſlaine the Saints of the moſt High, and witneſſes of Chriſt, and by his oppreſſion and cruelty. This voice was heard firſt from the whole Commons in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in whom all the power which is in Heaven did originally reſide, and afterwards in <hi>England,</hi> both from the whole Common-weale, and likewiſe from the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who ſate in Heaven,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.12.</note> 
                  <hi>And they aſcended up to Heaven,</hi> that is, they aſcended to the high place of Judicature, the ſame time 1639. in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and afterward here in <hi>England. They aſcended up in a cloud;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 4.16.</note> that is, in a time of great darkneſſe and ignorance, the whole world being overwhelmed with darkneſſe and ignorance; Likewiſe by a cloud and darkneſſe is ſet forth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joel</hi> 2.2.</note> a ſtate of miſery and diſtreſſe. And what miſery and diſtreſſe was the people of God in, and all the whole world at this very time, and therefore is truly ſaid, that they aſcended up in a cloud in a time of great ignorance and miſery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Chriſt is ſaid to come at this time in the clouds of Heaven, or in his Saints, to execute juddgement upon Antichriſt, with thoſe ſignes of his comming; very few of his Saints that have faith to beleeve this, only ſome few, who are counted wiſe.</head>
               <p>THe witneſſes being in Heaven,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.30.</note> the Lord Jeſus is to come in the clouds of Heaven to execute judgement upon that man of fin. By clouds is myſtically meant the witneſſes of Chriſt, in whom he is by his Spirit, as is noted in the Scripture of truth: When he is ſaid to come in the clouds of Heaven, he is ſaid at the ſame time to come with his Saints,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith, <hi>He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> like the Sonne of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> come in the clouds of Heaven,</hi> when the thrones of thoſe Beaſts or Kings were caſt down,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.3.</note> And <hi>Zechariah</hi> ſaith, when the Lord ſhall goe forth to fight againſt thoſe Kings that carried <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> captive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meaning the Church of God, whether <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> or <hi>Gentil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and by thoſe Kings he meanes thoſe foure Beaſts, and the little horne An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121084:15"/>then ſaith he, <hi>The Lord my God ſhall come;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 5.</note> 
                  <hi>and all his Saints with him;</hi> and when the Lord Chriſt ſpeaks of his comming to judge the enemies of the Church, and to deliver his people, he ſaith, <hi>That he ſhall come in the clouds of Heaven;</hi> and againe ſaith <hi>John,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.30.</note> 
                  <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold he commeth with clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him,</hi> and they that pierced him, meaning the Jewes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7.</note> who ſhall be brought to Chriſt in this age; and <hi>Enoch,</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Behold, the Lord commeth with</hi> 10000. <hi>of his Saints to execute judgement upon all for their ungodly deeds which they have committed, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">☜ </seg>
                  </label> The Saints of God and witneſſes of Chriſt that are now in Heaven are very fitly reſembled to clouds, in a two-fold reſpect: They ſerving for the ſame end and uſe in a myſticall and ſpirituall way, as clouds doe in a litterall and naturall way.</p>
               <p>Firſt, clouds are to keep us from the ſcorching and burning hear of the Sunne; ſo doe the clouds of our myſticall Heaven, the Saints of the moſt High, and Witneſſes of Chriſt keep the people of Chriſt from thoſe ſcorching and burning beames of that Antichriſtian Sunne, which hath burned many of the deare Saints of Chriſt to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es, and would doe the like to us at this time (being ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged with malice and fury as they are) if it were not for theſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall clouds that are fixed faſt in our Heaven.</p>
               <p>Secondly, clouds ſerve to carry water and moyſture to water and fatten the dry and barren earth, to make in fat and fruitfull: To the ſame end, in a myſticall and ſpirituall way, ſerve the clouds of our Heaven, not only to the Saints of God, but alſo to all other who have been dryed and parched by the heat of that Antichriſtian Sunne, even by his oppreſſion, tyranny and cruelty; and the clouds of our Heaven are to carry water that may refreſh the people of God and the whole land, I meane juſt and righteous lawes and ordinances, which may free us from thoſe great taxations and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions which wee meet with from Antichriſt, which hath been done in part, <hi>and were thoſe evill ſpirits which were raiſed by thoſe three unclean ſpirits like frogs which came out of the mouth of the falſe prophet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.13.</note> 
                  <hi>out of the mouth of the Dragon, and out of the mouth of the Beaſt,</hi> deſtroyed out of our land, we ſhould ſee ſuch great floods of waters flow from our clouds, as though the windowes of Heaven, and flood gates of the great Ocean were ſet open, foretold, and propheſied of by the ſervants of God, and therefore it is ſaid, <hi>The Lord will ſend downe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121084:16"/>bleſſings like raine upon the mowen graſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.6.</note> 
                  <hi>and as ſhowres that water the earth, the Valleys ſhall bring forth abundantly, and the hils ſhall drop down fatneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 3.</note> 
                  <hi>the mountaines ſhall bring peace to the people, and the little hils by righteouſneſſe.</hi> Thus we ſee the Saints and Witneſſes fitly reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to clouds, in whom the Lord Jeſus by his Spirit is come, and ſits upon the Throne to judge Antichriſt: we ſhall ſee it more plainly if we look into, and open thoſe foure ſignes which the Lord Chriſt gives us of his comming to judge Antichriſt. One ſigne is before his comming, another juſt at his comming, two after he is come. The ſignes before his comming is,<note place="margin">Firſt ſigne of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to judge Antichriſt.</note> the Sunne ſhall be darkned, and the Moon ſhall not give her light; we are not to underſtand this litteral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: at Chriſts firſt comming to judgement to judge Antichriſt, but at his laſt comming to judge quick and dead then it may be litterall, but not now; of thoſe two luminaries, but myſtically. Antichriſt is ſaid to have a world,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.13.</note> to aſcend up to Heaven: In this Heaven here is the Sunne, and Moon, and Starres, himſelfe being the Sunne, <hi>Oh Lucifer Sonne of the morning,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.12.</note> and his Cardinals that receive their light from him are the Moon, and the Prelats the Stars of this Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for they are in this Heaven, in the Houſe and Temple of God, where the Stars or Saints of God were, and they lorded it over all that was called Gods, as though they themſelves had been God, and they likewiſe ſit in the high place of judicature. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">☞ </seg>
                  </label> Now theſe two great lights of this Antichriſtian Heaven were darkned a little before Chriſt came in the clouds of Heaven; they began to grow darke in <hi>Luthers</hi> time, and in King <hi>Edward</hi> the fixths time, and likewiſe. Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, by the riſing and ſhining of that glorious Sunne of righteouſneſſe in the preaching of the Goſpels truth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.2.</note> and the more this Sunne ſhined, the more thoſe Antichriſtian lights grew paler and darker, untill the very time that he came in the clouds of Heaven; this ſigne before Chriſts comming was and is plainly fulfilled and accompliſhed before our eyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the ſigne at, and in the very inſtant time of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and this ſigne is in Heaven;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.30.</note> we are to keep the metaphor, not litterally to be underſtood for thoſe naturall Heavens, as many have ſuppoſed, and ſo have dreamed of a glorious light which was to ſhine or break forth from thoſe Heavens immediately before Chriſt came, which may be true at his laſt comming: But by thoſe Heavens or Heaven, is meant the Heaven or high place,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121084:16"/>where Antichriſt had his ſeat and throne: Firſt, he had his high place, where he ſate about Eccleſiaſticall affaires and Church mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, this is not the Heaven here meant. Secondly, he had his high place and throne, where he ſate to determine matters of the State and Common-weale,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.13.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Mount of the Congregation in the ſides of the North,</hi> where the Judges of the civill law were wont to ſit in ancient time; this is the Heaven or high place where the ſigne of the Son of man is to appeare, immediately at his comming in the clouds of Heaven: and this ſigne was nothing elſe but that ſudden alteration that was in this Heaven, the day or yeer the Witneſſes aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended up to this Heaven, in the yeere before 1638. Pope and Prelate ſate as ſole Judges in this Heaven, over the Saints and people of God; but 1639. the Witneſſes are raiſed up to this Heaven in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſit as Lord and Judges of them, who by a ſolemn Oath made with the moſt high God, caſt out Pope and Prelate out of Heaven: never to have to do or to meddle with Church or State af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faire, but to be caſt from Heaven, as the Spirit of God foretold;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.2.</note> 
                  <hi>How art thou fallen from Heaven O Lucifer ſonne of the morning, and how art thou cut downe to the ground, which didſt weaken the Nations:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.9.</note> and againe; <hi>The great Dragon was caſt out into the earth, and his Angels with him.</hi> This is the ſigne of the Sonne of man in Heaven, which appeares plainly by this which our Saviour notes to be at the ſame time: <hi>Then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall all the Tribes of the earth mourne, when they ſee the Sonne of man come in the clouds of Heaven.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.30. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7.</note> Was not this very evident? did not all the Tribes of that Antichriſtian earth mourn when they ſee the godly party not onely to ſtand upon their feet, which had lien dead three yeers and a halfe? but now ſeeing them aſcend to the high place of Judicature, they were filled with feare and ſorrow, ſuppoſing ſome dreadfull thing would follow: The Popes Maſter-piece witneſſeth at large, what feare and ſorrow was not onely here amongſt the Antichriſtian party, but at <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the third ſigne was, <hi>that the Starres ſhould fall from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> By Starres,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.29.</note> we ſhewed was meant thoſe leſſer lights of that Antichriſtian Heaven, which was popiſh Lords and Prelats, which were as fixed Starres of this Heaven; they fell downe to the earth (not to have any more power in the Church or State) in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the yeer 1639. and in <hi>England</hi> 1641. and ſhall fall from Heaven
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121084:17"/>in all the other eight Kingdomes of the Beaſt very ſhortly.</p>
               <p>The fourth and laſt ſigne of Chriſts comming in the clouds of Heaven to judge Antichriſt,<note place="margin">The fourth ſigne. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.25.</note> is the roaring of the Sea; <hi>The Sea and the waves thereof ſhall roare,</hi> we are to keep to the metaphor: Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt had a world, in that world he had his Heavens and lights therein, and he hath an earth and ſea: by ſea in a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall way is meant,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.1, 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.6.</note> nothing elſe but many waters gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther metaphorically, and myſtically many people, multitudes, and nations, and tongues; and theſe are ſaid to rage and roare when Jeſus Chriſt in his Saints are about to bind the wicked with cords, <hi>their Kings in chaines, and Nobles in fetters of iron,</hi> and when God is about to ſet his King upon his holy hill of <hi>Sion.</hi> And have not we ſeene the Heathen and the Antichriſtian party rage and fume even like the waves of the Sea, as though they would overwhelme and beare downe all before them? but yet this their rage is nothing, or but very little to what will be in all the other eight Kingdoms: Oh how will they rage and lift up their waves to Heaven when Chriſt and his witneſſe ſhall come to poure forth the fifth Viall upon the ſeat and throne of the Beaſt, and the ſixt Viall upon the River <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates</hi> amongſt them there, which will be as ſoone as they have poured them forth here.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.30.</note> Thus have we ſeene theſe foure great ſignes of Chriſt comming to judge Antichriſt in the clouds of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in part fulfilled before our eyes, <hi>And be is ſaid to come in power and great glory.</hi> This glory is not an outward luſter, or glory as ſome have ſupoſed to be in the firmament,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.27. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6. <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.19.</note> which may be true at his laſt comming, but a myſticall and ſpirituall glory at this time, even the glory of God his Father. The ſame glory which God ſhewed unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he defired to ſee his glory, which was called all his goodneſſe or excellency, which indeed is the glory of all his Attibutes; and in this glory Chriſt is ſaid to come at this time, when he came in myſticall clouds.</p>
               <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.12.</note> he is ſaid to come in power: What great power did Chriſt manifeſt in raiſing up his Saints and Witneſſes from ſuch a low ſtate, a ſtate of death, and to ſet them upon their feet by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that entred into them the yeere 1639. and raiſed them up to Heaven and caſt their enemies out. Here was the glory of his great power ſeene,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rach.</hi> 4, 6.</note> as the holy Ghoſt ſaith, not by power of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or by the might of a fleſhly arme was they raiſed up to Heaven, but by the Spirit of God.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:121084:17"/>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8.</note> the glory of Gods mercy did ſhine forth in delivering his Saints and people, which were in a ſuch miſerable condition, <hi>who were ſlain, and lay as dead men in the ſtreets of that ſpirituall</hi> Sodom, <hi>&amp; their dead bodies not ſuffered to be put into graves;</hi> for the Lord Jeſus to ſend his ſpirit of life into them, &amp; to ſet them upon their feet, and to raiſe them up to Heaven, whereby they were freed from the rage of their enemies, and made Lords and Judges over them, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their enemies as they rewarded them, yea, to returne them double:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6.</note> Oh the glory of the mercy of Jeſus Chriſt towards his poor ſervants.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the glory of Gods wiſdome was much ſeen in this great work, to doe it at ſuch a time when his people could not ſee how or by which way they ſhould be delivered; &amp; Antichriſt thinking himſelf to be now ſecurer, and ſafely ſeated in peace &amp; tranquility,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.10.</note> 
                  <hi>rejoycing and ſending gifts one to another, becauſe thoſe two Prophets were ſlain which tormented them.</hi> The wiſdome of God now ſtept in at the very nick and point of time, and by his wiſdome makes this to be the onely and chiefe time of the beginning of the enemies downfall, and the Churches deliverance. Oh the admirable and unſpeakable glory of Chriſts wiſdome! his wiſdome is infinite, and there is no ſearching of his underſtanding!</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the glory of Gods free grace and love were wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſted; there was no worth nor deſert in his ſervants to move him to have pitty or compaſſion on them in ſuch a low con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: All that they did in the days of their propheſie and giving teſtimony was but their duty, and in all they were but unprofitable ſervants: and therefore what the Lord did to them and for them at this time was of his free grace and love;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.7.</note> therefore well may we with ſhouting cry <hi>Grace, grace, unto this great worke.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 18.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, the glory of his truth and faithfulneſſe appeares in making good his Word and promiſes unto his Church and people, which he hath made often in the Scripture of truth, and in performing his Word and threatnings againſt the enemies of his Church.</p>
               <p>The glory of his juſtice and holineſſe ſhineth forth with much glory and brightneſſe,<note place="margin">verſe 6.</note> in executing juſtice upon ſuch an ancient enemy of the Church, which with his predeceſſors hath been an enemy this 2300 yeers almoſt; and ſo cruell and malicious an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who hath <hi>magnified himſelfe to the Hoaſt of Heaven, yea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>to the Prince of the Hoaſt,</hi> and caſt him from his Throne, taken his Crown
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121084:18"/>from his head, caſt him and his Spouſe out of his Houſe and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſtrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her of her robes, and would have forced her to commit ſpirituall fornication, and broken the Church all to pieces, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured many of them, and trampled the reſt under his feet; and laſt of all, ſlaine the Witneſſes of Chriſt, and laid their dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in the ſtreets, not ſuffering them to be put into graves; all this villany hath he done to the Saints; and for the people of the Antichriſtian earth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ya.</hi> 4.16, 17.</note> whom he hath reigned over ſo long; <hi>he hath made the very earth to tremble, and did ſhake Kingdomes, the world he made as a Wilderneſſe, and destroyed the Cities thereof by his tyranny and oppreſſion, and looſed not the houſe of his priſoners.</hi> Doth not the glory of Chriſts juſtice and ſeverity appeare wonderfully in the ruine and utter deſtruction of ſuch a grand, notorious, cruell, malicious, and inſolent an enemy as this? and the glory of his holineſſe in deſtroying ſuch a filthy Whore and Strumpet as Antichriſt is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.2.</note> 
                  <hi>who hath committed ſpirituall fornication with all the Kings of the earth, and the Inhabiters of the earth have been made drunke with the wine of her fornication;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.4.</note> therefore ſaith the Scripture, <hi>who ſhall not feare thee, and glorifie thy name, for thou onely art holy, and all Nations ſhall worſhip before thee, for thy judgements are made manifeſt,</hi> and againe, <hi>True and righteous are his judgements, for he hath judged the great Whore which did corrupt the earth with her fornications,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and hath avenged the blood of his ſervants at her hands.</hi> In the glory of theſe great Attributes is the Lord Jeſus come, and they have ſhined forth in ſome meaſure to the joy, and comfort, and ſalvation of his people, and to the ſorrow and deſtruction of his enemies: But when the Lord Chriſt ſhall come to the end of this great work of his in the utter ruine of his enemies, and perfect deliverance of his Church; then will the glory of theſe Attributes ſhine forth with ſuch glory and ſplendor as ſhall darken the eye of the cleareſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and affect the moſt flinty heart, putting them to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration and aſtoniſhment. But this the Spirit of God notes in the Scripture,<note place="margin">☞ <hi>Luke</hi> 18.8.</note> that when Chriſt ſhall come to avenge his Elect, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this very time, which is the time of the enemies utter ruine, and the Churches ſmall deliverance, he ſhall hardly find faith upon the earth; he meanes, he ſhall hardly find faith in his Saints concerning the enemies ruine and their deliverance, and not juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying faith; intimating to us, that the Church ſhall be brought ſo
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121084:18"/>low, as they ſhall not have faith enough to raiſe them ſo high, as to look to God for their deliverance through ſo many difficulties.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.9.</note> This time &amp; myſtery was hid from all former ages, and the words cloſed up and ſealed untill the time of the end, &amp; <hi>written in a little book, and ſealed with ſeven ſeals, none being able to open it neither in Heaven or earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7.</note> 
                  <hi>or under the earth, but Chriſt only, &amp; it is called, The great Mystery of God, not opened till the ſeventh Trumpet begins to ſound;</hi> and we doe not read he began to ſound untill the Witneſſes were in Heaven, and the tenth part of the City fell, which was the yeere of Chriſt 1639<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at which time God promiſeth <hi>it ſhall ſpeake and not lye,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3.</note> as indeed it did ſpeak if we could have heard it and underſtood it.</p>
               <p>But ſaith the Lord, <hi>None of the wicked ſhall understand,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.10.</note> 
                  <hi>but the wiſe ſhall understand;</hi> none of the wicked ſhall underſtand,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.10, 11, 12.</note> Prieſts nor Prophets, Rulers nor Seers, all hid &amp; covered, &amp; the viſion is become to them all as a ſealed book, if one deſire them to read, they cannot, it is ſealed but the Lord gives many reaſons why theſe wiſe &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctors &amp; Rabbies could not underſtand the viſion of the time of the end when it is to ſpeak, and to be made plain upon Tables.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.2, 3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29, 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>becauſe they are drunke, but not with Wine; they stagger, but not with ſtrong drinke.</hi> This drunkenneſſe is not a drunkenneſſe with naturall wine, but it is a ſpirituall drunkenneſſe with the wine of that ſpirituall fornication,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.2.</note> with which that Antichriſtian Whore hath filled her cup, and made them drunke with it, therefore they erre in viſion and ſtumble in judgement.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.10.</note> they having drunk of this wine of ſpirituall fornication now a deep ſleep of ſecurity and ſpirituall ſtupidity hath ſeazed on them, and ſo cannot make uſe of their underſtanding nor learning in ſuch a ſpirituall way, as to come to underſtand a viſion or my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of God: It is true, there is darkneſſe as well as light,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.6, 7.</note> but if it were not for this ſpirituall ſlumber, they might ſee as well as others though the light be not cleare.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Becauſe they draw nigh to God with their lips,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 13.</note> 
                  <hi>but their hearts is farre from him.</hi> Teaching men to feare God by their owne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and commands; <hi>Therefore the Lord will proceed to do a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious worke amongſt this people, even a marvellous worke and a wonder, for the wiſdome of the wiſe man ſhall periſh, and the underſtanding of the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſhall be hid; yea, ſuch a marvellous worke ſhall be done in their daies, that they will not beleeve it though it be told them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.5.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:121084:19"/>
               <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe they ſeek deep to hide their counſels from the Lord, and their works are in the darke, and they ſay, Who ſeeth? or who knoweth?</hi> They by their owne policy &amp; craft did take counſell together to mingle their owne water with the Saints wine, and their droſſe with the people of Gods ſilver,<note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note> their owne traditions with Gods inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and for this they digged deep, wrought in the darke, and hid their craft from Gods people, and ſaid in their hearts, Who ſeeth us?<note place="margin">Verſ. 16</note> or who knoweth? &amp; by this means they are ſaid to turn the worſhip of God up ſide downe, even quite overthrow the whole worſhip of God, and to make his Law of none effect. But ſaith the Lord, <hi>It ſhall be counted as Potters clay,</hi> at the end all broken to pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and never ſet together againe. Thus none of the wicked ſhall underſtand, nor but few of the Saints, (only the wiſe.) The wiſe, they ſhall underſtand; <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.10. we are to finde out who are ſaid to be wiſe in this ſenſe, which the Spirit of God ſpeakes of in this place: This is not that wiſdome which makes a man wiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſalvation, (for with that all the people of God are inveſted,) but it is that wiſdome which the wiſe man ſpeakes of,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>To underſtand a Proverbe, and the interpretation thereof, the words of the wiſe, and their darke ſaying.</hi> Which is to be done two waies.</p>
               <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.2.</note> by ſearching and ſeriouſly pondering the bookes and the roles of the Proverbs and Viſion, as <hi>Daniel</hi> did, which ſpeakes of the viſion and myſtery which God hath ſhewed to his Prophets, and they that do ſo are bleſſed of God, and wiſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, and they that ſecretly eye God in thoſe ſecret and hidden acts of his providence, by which he uſually makes a viſion to ſpeak,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.43.</note> and makes it plaine upon tables, <hi>Who ſo is wiſe and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth theſe things,</hi> ſaith the Text, what things? why? they were the acts of Gods providence all the Pſalme over, <hi>Even they ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the loving kindneſſe of God to his Church and people.</hi> And who are thoſe? you have ſeen they are none of the great Rabbies and Doctors of our age, but ſuch <hi>that are weaned from the milke, and drawn from the breaſts;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.9.</note> thoſe young babes of Chriſt that have not drunke of that filthy abominable cup of that Antichriſtian Whore: Them will the Lord teach knowledge, and inſtruct in the way of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they that have not dranke or ſipped of that Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian cup, but hath overcome that beaſt and Whore with all their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121084:19"/>abominable errors and hereſies, to them hath Chriſt promiſed to give the morning Starre, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.28.</p>
               <p>By Starre cannot be meant Chriſt, as ſome have ſuppoſed, for there is none able to overcome Antichriſt, his marke or number of his traditions, brought in by his power, which is called his name; but he muſt firſt be made one with Chriſt by faith, and draw and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive power and ſtrength from him to enable him thereunto; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by morning Starre is meant ſome thing elſe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.14.</note> The morning Star doth riſe before the day come an houre or two, to give notice the day is not far off, but nigh at hand. So the Lord Chriſt by his Spiritin thoſe ſecret waies of his providence, will give to thoſe his ſervants that overcome Antichriſt, the bright morning Star: That is, will diſcover ſuch a light to them, as ſhall be as the morning Star, to give them notice that the glorious day of Jeſus Chriſt ſhall ſhortly appeare, wherein he and his Saints ſhall raigne in peace and tranquility for 1000. yeares. Thus thoſe that are wiſe ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and they that overcome ſhall ſee the firſt dawning of that glorious day of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>God doth ſo loath that abominable cup of ſpirituall fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that whoſoever drinks or ſips thereof; ſhall not lye ſo neare Chriſts heart, as to have the viſion or myſtery made knowne to him; no, they that are the young men, they ſhall ſee viſions, even the young babes of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.16.</note> 
                  <hi>that out of the mouthes of babes and ſucklings he may perfect praiſe:</hi> This viſion is both meant of Chriſts comming in the fleſh, and of his comming to judge An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt; and none of thoſe great Doctors and Rabbies did under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand when Chriſt ſhould come in the fleſh; but the young men and poore men, they underſtood and beleeved. And ſo it is with this preſent age; who will beleeve of all our great men, and learned Prelates, that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the clouds of Heaven, and is ſet downe upon the throne of Judicature in his Saints and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to judge that man of ſin?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:121084:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The ſeventh Chapter openeth the ſeven Seales, Trumpets, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ials; ſhewing that they are all about one and the ſame thing.</head>
               <p>THat great miſtery of God, concerning the ruine of all thoſe enemies of the Church,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>is written within a little books, Rev.</hi> 5.1. and this booke <hi>is in the hand of Chriſt, who ſits upon the throne,</hi> and it hath <hi>ſeven plagnes written within it,</hi> (ſeven is a number of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,) a perfect number of plagues to be poured upon the enemies of Gods Church,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.3.45.</note> to their utter ruine. Theſe ſeven plagues are as it were written in ſeven ſheets of parchment, and rolled up together, and ſealed with ſeven ſeales, as the manner and cuſtome of the <hi>Jewes</hi> was, in all buſineſſes of great conſequence: The ſeven Seales could not be opened by any,<note place="margin">Verſ. 8, 9.10.</note> neither in Heaven, or Earth, or under the Earth, but Chriſt only, <hi>the Lion of the Tribe of Judah;</hi> and <hi>he is counted worthy to open this booke, by the foure Beaſt, &amp; the foure and twenty Elders, and to looſe the ſeven ſeales thereof:</hi> Whereupon they ſing a new ſong to God and the Lambe, giving him glory, becauſe he had been ſlaine, and had not onely redeemed them from wrath, hell, and eternall death, but alſo from the ſlavery and bondage of wicked and ungodly men; yea, <hi>out of all Nations, tongues and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and made them unto God Kings and Prieſts, and they ſhall raigne with Chriſt upon the Earth</hi> in peace a thouſand yeares: this is that new Song that they ſung, and it is ſung againe by thoſe ſealed ones of God, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.4. by the 144000. <hi>Which are upon Mount Sion with the Lambe, Rev.</hi> 14.1. Hence note the quick eye of the Saints faith, as ſoon as Chriſt takes this booke in his hand, they looke upon the worke as done, as though their enemies had been quite ruinated and themſelves delivered; they looke from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the end of the worke; Chriſt is to open this book, and to breake open theſe ſeven ſeales, and no other. But there are ſeven Angels with ſeven Trumpets to ſound, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.2. who were to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelves to ſound, <hi>ver.</hi> 6, when the ſeales were to be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt, to declare and make knowne what was written with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Roll, even what the viall was which was to be poured up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Antichriſtian ſtate.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:121084:20"/>
               <p>And here is likewiſe ſeven Angels appointed to poure forth thoſe ſeven vials upon Antichriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.6, 7. which were full of the wrath of God.</p>
               <p>When Chriſt opened the firſt Seale, then the firſt Angel ſounded his Trumpet, and the firſt Angel poured out the firſt Viall, and ſo the ſecond, and third, to the ſeventh; the Seales, Trumpets, Vials, all about one and the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the ſeven Seales ſerved only to keep thoſe things ſecret which were written within the rolls. The Trumpet or Trumpets, to ſound and to declare what the Vials were, that were written within the roll, or rolls: The Angel or Angels to poure forth the Viall or Vials upon that Anthriſtian ſtate.</p>
               <p>That you may ſee this more plainly, we will open and explaine the Seales, Trumpets, and Vials, and compare them one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſee how they agree.</p>
               <p>At the opening the firſt Seale by the Lamb,<note place="margin">Firſt Seale is opened. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>John</hi> heard the noiſe of thunder. When the Lord Chriſt goes out firſt to make war againſt thoſe grand enemies of his Church, he thunders &amp; is very tertible; he had a bow given him, which notes war againſt that antichriſtian Earth, as yee ſhall ſee by the Trumpet and Viall; and he is upon a white horſe, and he hath a Crown given him, which notes both his innocency and victory, therefore he is ſaid to go forth conquering to conquer.</p>
               <p>This Seale agrees with the firſt trumpet,<note place="margin">Firſt Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſoundeth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.7.</note> that when it ſounded <hi>Then came haile and fire mingled with blood, and they were caſt upon that Antichriſtian Earth,</hi> even the men of the Earth, that ſeemed to be <hi>living trees and green graſſe,</hi> but were burned up by the preaching of the Goſpel. In this we are to note, that the ſounding of the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets is nothing elſe but the preaching of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>This Seale and Trumpet agrees with the firſt Viall which was poured upon that antichriſtian Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.2.<note place="margin">Firſt Viall is poured forth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.2.</note> 
                  <hi>And there fell upon the men of that Earth, which had received the marke of the Beaſt, and that worſhipped his Image even a noyſome ſore.</hi> By the preaching of the Goſpell by the Angels, or Miniſters of the Churches, theſe men appeared very loath ſome and vile unto all godly and ſober minded men, even they who had received the marke of the beaſt, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped his Image, and thus Chriſt goes out with a <hi>how in his hand, conquering to conquer,</hi> beginning firſt with that antichriſtian Earth.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:121084:21"/>
               <p>When the ſecond Seal was opened,<note place="margin">Second Seale is opened. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.3.</note> there appeared <hi>a red horſe, which betokens blood, and it was given to him to take peace from the men of this Antichristian earth, and that they ſhould kill one another,</hi> as indeed they did, by their impure and curſed doctrine, as we ſhall ſee anon, <hi>and a great ſword was given unto him,</hi> which was the ſword of the Goſpell as we ſhall ſee noted by the ſecond Trumpet.</p>
               <p>And when the ſecond Trumpet ſounded there appeared a <hi>great mountaine burning with fire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Second Trumpet ſoundeth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.8.</note> 
                  <hi>which was caſt into the ſea, and the third part of the ſea became blood, and the third part of the creatures that were in the ſea, that had life, died, and the third part of the ſhips were deſtroyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the ſecond Angel preached the Goſpell, then a great mountaine burned with fire: By mountaine is meant power, great power was given to the Miniſters in ſounding this ſecond Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and this power burned upon that Antichriſts ſea like fire; by ſea is meant the doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and they by the preaching the Goſpell againſt that ſea or doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome, the third part of it became as blood.</hi> Bloody doctrine, ſo that they that ſeeme to live in this ſea before, now dyed, yea, now it appeares that they ſpiritually deſtroyed one another by this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure and poyſonous doctrine; <hi>and the third part of the ſhips</hi> that traded upon this ſea, or traded with this doctrine are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</p>
               <p>This Seale and Trumpet agrees with the ſecond Viall fully,<note place="margin">Second Viall poured forth.</note> 
                  <hi>which was poured upon the ſea,</hi> and it became as the blood of a dead man, and every living ſoule firſt and laſt, that dranke of this curſedand poyſenous doctrine of the ſea of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſpiritually dyed.</p>
               <p>And when Chriſt had opened the third Seale,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.3. Third Seale opened. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>loe a black horſe: which betokened death,</hi> as we ſhall ſee anon; <hi>and he that ſate upon him had a paire of balances in his hand, and a voyce cryes in the midſt of the foure Officers of the Church, and ſayes, A meaſure of Wheat for a penny, and three meaſures of Barly for a penny, and ſee thou hurt not the Oyle and Wine,</hi> Chriſt here hath a pair of balances in his hand, as a righteous and juſt Judge, to weigh all thoſe wrongs and injuries which thoſe Prieſts and Jeſuits had done againſt his Saints and ſervants, and he will repay them accordingly, therefore ſaith the voyce, <hi>A mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Wheat for a penny, and three meaſures of Barly,</hi> but no hurt muſt come to the Saints, that are the Oyle and Wine of the earth.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:121084:21"/>
               <p>And this we ſhall ſee agree with the third Trumpet and Viall,<note place="margin">Third Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſounds. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.10, 11.</note> the Trumpet when it ſounds, <hi>Then there fell a great Starre from Heaven, burning as it were a lampe, and it fell upon the third part of the Rivers and Fountaines of water, and the name of the Starre is called Wormwood, and the third part of the waters became Wormwood, and many men dyed of the waters, becauſe they were made bitter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By Starre, is meant an Angell or Miniſter of the Church, ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20. by Heaven is meant the Church, by Rivers or Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of waters is meant, thoſe Jeſuits and Prieſts that are ſet forth by Rivers and Fountaines of waters, who naturally draw and derive water from the Sea to water the Earth; ſo doe they myſtically as Rivers draw and derive their poyſonous doctrine from that Antichriſtian Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo water the whole Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian earth. The Miniſters of the Churches by the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpell ſhined as a Lamp; and theſe Rivers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come blood, noted by the the third Viall, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.4. and likewiſe made their doctrine to be bitter and loathſome, ſhewing that they by their poyſonous doctrine did ſeduce the people, and ſpiritually ſlayed men; yea further, by their doctrine had ſtirred up the Beaſt and his Image to ſlay the Saints and Prophets of Chriſt, as is noted by the third Angell that poured forth his Viall upon them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.5, 6. therefore they themſelves became blood; that is, their blood is ſhed, and they are put to death in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, and ſince, and as Maſter <hi>Cotton</hi> well obſerves; thus Chriſt weighs the wrongs done to his Saints by theſe Prieſts and Jeſuits, who are thoſe Antichriſtian Rivers and Fountaines of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſo repayes them accordingly.</p>
               <p>This Seale and Trumpet agrees fully with the <hi>third Viall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The third Viall is pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red forth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.4.</note> 
                  <hi>which was poured upon the Rivers and Fountaines of waters, ſo that they became blood,</hi> not onely appeared by the ſounding of the Trumpet to be bloody men, ſuch as thirſted after the blood of Gods Saints, but their owne blood was ſhed, for they were worthy, as the Angell of the waters well notes, becauſe they had cauſed the blood of the Saints to be ſhed, therefore God was juſt and righteous becauſe he had ſo judged, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.5, 6.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>Lambe opens the fourth Seale, behold a pale horſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fourth Seale opened. <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.7.</note> 
                  <hi>which notes darkneſſe and miſery, and he that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> upon it was Death.</hi> Now Chriſt threatens death unto that whole Antichriſtian ſtate,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121084:22"/>the lights of their Heaven grow pale and darke, as is noted by the Angel that ſounded the Trumpet, and that poured forth the fourth Viall, <hi>and Death and Hell followed with him; and afterward power was given to him over the fourth part of the Earth, to kill with the ſword, with hunger and death, and the Beasts of the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This horſe was <hi>a pale horſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fourth An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell ſounds. <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.12.</note> betokening blackneſſe and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as is noted by the fourth Angel that ſounded, that when he ſounds, <hi>the the third part of the Sunne, Moon, and Starres of that Antichristian Heaven,</hi> Pope, Cardinals and Prelats, glorious lights of that Heaven, when this fourth Angel preacheth the Goſpell, the late Miniſters of our foregoing Age, theſe lights loſt the third part of their glory, and ſhined not ſo bright as they did before by the third part.</p>
               <p>The fourth Angel which poured forth the fourth Viall agrees with this Seale and Trumpet,<note place="margin">The fourth Viall poured forth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.8.</note> 
                  <hi>who poured his Viall upon that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian Sunne,</hi> and ſo notes to us, that all the other lights of that Heaven were darkned with it, becauſe they drew their lights from it in a myſticall way, as the Moone and Starres doe in a naturall way from the naturall Sunne.</p>
               <p>The Miniſters of Chriſt by preaching the Goſpell, darkned theſe glorious lights of that Antichriſtian Heaven; and by ſo doing <hi>ſcorched and burned them with fire;</hi> that is, put them to as much paine and torment as though they had ſcorched them with naturall fire, whereupon they blaſphemed the name of God; that is, ſpoke more evilly of the wayes and Saints of God, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded more harſhly and bitterly againſt them, even to their civill ſlaying, and lay their dead bodies in the ſtreets.</p>
               <p>That death and hell followed upon the fourth Seal, Trumpet and Viall, is noted by an Angel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.13. <hi>which flies through the midſt of Heaven, crying, Woe, woe, woe:</hi> Three woes, becauſe of thoſe three Angels which were to ſound, and three Vials which were to be poured forth upon that Antichriſtian ſtate to its utter ruine.</p>
               <p>When Chriſt had opened the fifth Seale,<note place="margin">The fifth Seal is opened. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9.</note> the ſoules under the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar come to ſee what was written within the Roll, and there they ſee Chriſt and his Witneſſes aſcend up to Heaven, the high place of Judicature, to take the Kingdomes and powers from Antichriſt preſently,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>they cry for vengeance upon them that had ſhed their blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:121084:22"/>
               <p>Theſe ſouls are the Saints of God in our age which ſee themſelves ſlaine, for the word of God, and the teſtimony which they held: By <hi>word of God</hi> is meant Chriſt, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. and 14. and <hi>their testimony</hi> is their bearing witneſſe unto thoſe truths of Chriſt which Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt denied, their ſlaying was civill, all power taken from them, that they could not propheſie nor give teſtimony to the truths of Chriſt, as they had formerly done; <hi>they are ſaid to be under the Altar,</hi> by Altar is meant Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.10.</p>
               <p>They were under his ſpirituall power and juriſdiction, though civilly ſlain by Antichriſt, and laid dead for three dayes and a half; theſe ſoules that ſee themſelves ſlaine, <hi>had white robes given them</hi> by Chriſt and his witneſſe in that ſpace of time that the fifth Viall was pouring forth.</p>
               <p>By white robes cannot be meant the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, inherent or imputed for that they had before, which made them to undergoe that flory try all, and ſuffer civill marty dome; which righteouſneſſe is ſet forth by gold tryed in the fire,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.18. but theſe white robes is that outward government and diſcipline that is to be ſet up in all the Churches of the Saints, ſet forth by white rayment: Fine gold make the Saints ſpirituall, rich, and enable them to endure the fiery tryall; eye-ſalve cleares the eyes of their underſtandings, that they thereby come to ſee the way of Chriſt in his houſe and Temple, in what way he will be worſhipped; white rayment is the government and diſcipline of the Church, which is to cover the ſhame of the Churches nakedneſſe, that it doth not appeare unto the world; every member of the Church, and the Church her ſelfe walking according to the rule and order of the Goſpel.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15, 16, 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>We ſhall ſee this Seale agree with the fifth Trumpet and fifth Viall in the ſenſe of it.</p>
               <p>The fifth Angel ſounding, a Star fals from Heaven unto the Earth,<note place="margin">The fifth Trumpet ſounds. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> &amp; unto him was given the <hi>Key</hi> of the bottomles pit. <hi>By Star</hi> is meant a Miniſter or Miniſters of Chriſt; by <hi>Heaven</hi> is meant the Church; by <hi>Key</hi> is meant power, by <hi>bottomleſſe pit</hi> is meant the depth of the craft and ſubtilty of that nian of ſin in his curſed doctrine &amp; traditions.</p>
               <p>So the Miniſters of the Churches were inveſted with power from Chriſt in the preaching of the Goſpel, to open the depth of Satan and Antichriſt in his curſed doctrine ferched out of that bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121084:23"/>pit, eſpecially concerning the uſurpation of his power.</p>
               <p>Whereupon commeth a great ſmoak, noting thereby darkneſſe, and therefore it is ſaid, <hi>That the Sunne and Aire was filled with dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and in <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.10. when the fifth Viall was poured out, it ſaid, <hi>His Kingdome was full of darkneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>ſmoake</hi> notes miſery likewiſe, therefore <hi>Locusts are ſaid to come out of the ſmoake, unto whom was given power, as the Scorpions of the earth have power, and they were to torment the men of that Antichristian world five moneths;</hi> a certaine time ſet downe for an uncertaine; and their torment is very ſore, as when a Scorpion ſtriketh a man, that they ſhall ſeek death and ſhall not find it.</p>
               <p>This is noted further, that theſe Locuſts were like unto horſes prepared unto battell, when Chriſt and his Saints take the power of Churches and States from Antichriſt, it is to be pre-ſuppoſed that Antichriſt will preſently raiſe a very great Army to make warre with them, as ye ſhall ſee anon fall out to be ſo, by the ſounding of the next Trumpet.</p>
               <p>But theſe men that was counted as Locuſts unto Antichriſt, they have Crownes of gold, to note their victory; if Antichriſt ſhould make warre with them, and they have faces like men, to note their Majeſty and authority, and haire as the haire of women, to note their terribleneſſe and fearceneſſe, and teeth of Lyons, to note their greedineſſe, to prey upon theſe Antichriſtian men, to eat their fleſh,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.17.</note> and to burne them with fire.</p>
               <p>And breſt-plats of iron to note their ſtrength to encounter with him, the ſound of their wings being as the ſound of Chariots, of many horſes running to battaile, and their tailes like unto Scorpions to torment them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.12.</note> and to put them unto grievous paine, and he that is King over them is the Angel of the bottomleſſe pit, even the Lord Chriſt, ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.1, 2. that will ere long caſt the Beaſt and that falſe Prophet into it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.10. yea, and the Devil himſelfe, and ſhut him up and ſet a ſeale upon it, binding him for a thouſand yeers, <hi>verſe.</hi> 1, 2. Thus the firſt woe is paſt, and behold there commeth two woes more herereafter.</p>
               <p>The fifth Angell poured forth the fifth Viall,<note place="margin">The fifth Vial. poured forth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.10. upon the ſeate of the Beaſt, and then they gnawed their tongues for paine.</p>
               <p>And all this torment was when the fifth Angel poured forth his
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121084:23"/>Viall upon the ſeat and throne of the Beaſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.12. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.26.</note> even when the Lord Chriſt and his witneſſes aſcended up into Heaven, 1639. and when the judgement ſate, and tooke his Kingdome and Dominions from him. For wicked and ungodly men to be taken from their high places of honour, it is as great a torment to them, as when a Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion ſtriketh a man; when Pope, Cardinall, and Prelates, are caſt from the high place of Judicature, they that do it are as Locuſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and their torment is inſufferable, they gnaw their tongues for paine, and they deſire to die, and death flees from them.</p>
               <p>When the ſixth Seale was opened, <hi>Behold a great earth-quake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sixth Seale opened. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.12.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Sun became black as haire-cloath, and the Moon as blood, and the ſtars fall from Heaven unto the Earth, and the Heaven departed as a ſcroll, when it is rolled together, and every mountaine and Iſland were moved out of their places, and the Kings and great men and mighty men of the Earth hide themſelves in dens and in the rocks of the mountaines, that they might be hid from the face of Chriſt that ſits upon the throne, becauſe the great day of his wrath is come, and they will never be able to abide it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt and his witneſſes being upon the throne, takes away Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts Kingdome and Dominions from him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.7.</note> whereupon there fals out to be war between Chriſt and Antichriſt, foretold by the fifth Trumpet: In this war there followes a great earth-quake, a great ſlaughter amongſt the men of that Antichriſtian Earth, and the Pope, the ſun of this heaven, becomes black as haire-cloath,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.13.</note> and his Cardinals ſet forth by the Moon, become as blood; and Popiſh Lords and Prelates, ſet forth by Stars, fals from Heaven, thoſe high places where they had their ſeate and throne, even <hi>above the ſtars of Gods,</hi> in Gods Houſe and Temple, and in the civill throne, <hi>upon the Mount of the Congregation.</hi> After they are fallen from Heaven; their Heaven fel with them, and is rolled together as a ſcroll, and all their Mountaines and power of States and Iſlands is moved out of their place, and ſet in their right place. And in this battell and earthquake Kings &amp; the great men of the world crie to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to fall upon them, and to hide them from the face of the Lambe the Lord Chriſt, becauſe now the great day of his wrath is come, in which he will take geance upon all theſe five grand ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of his Church, and upon that Antichriſtian world.</p>
               <p>But this is noted in <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.1, 2, 3, 4. that at this time in the midſt of all this wrath and fury of Chriſt againſt this wicked antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121084:24"/>crue; he takes care of his Elect &amp; choſen people, (eſpecially thoſe that are in a true Church-ſtate) as the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was, (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſet forth by them) &amp; who are ſaid to be upon Mount <hi>Sion</hi> with the Lambe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1. ſinging a new Song; theſe muſt be all ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and have the marke of God ſet in their foreheads;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.1, 2 3, 4.</note> therefore thoſe foure Angels that ſtands upon the foure corners of the Earth, to hold the foure windes of Gods wrath in their hands, ready to blow upon that antichriſtian World, muſt not let thoſe windes blow, untill an Angel hath ſealed the ſervants of Chriſt, <hi>and there was ſealed</hi> 144000. the ſame number that are upon Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> in a true Church-ſtate, with the Lambe the Lord Chriſt, their Lord and King, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1.</p>
               <p>This ſixth Trumpet appeares to be one and the ſame with the ſixth Seale;<note place="margin">Sixth Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſounds. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9, 14.</note> when this Trumpet ſounds <hi>Thoſe foure Angels which were bound in that great river</hi> Euphrates <hi>is looſed for an houre, day, moneth, and yeare, to ſlay the third part of thoſe antichriſtian men,</hi> a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine time for an uncertaine, as is ſuppoſed about the ſpace of 14. yeares, beginning in 1641. and ends 1655.</p>
               <p>By foure Angels is meant a certaine company of men, inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Gods wrath to deſtroy Antichriſt and his great Army; the number of theſe men are ſet downe in the next Verſe, to be <hi>two hundred thouſand thouſand:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.15.</note> By river <hi>Euphrates,</hi> is meant myſtically, a great company <hi>of People, Nations, and Tongues,</hi> on which that antichriſtian Whore did ſit; and amongſt thoſe was theſe inſtruments of Gods wrath bound, by that civill power which Antichriſt had in his hand,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.16.</note> before the witneſſe aſcended up into Heaven, but after they were aſcended, and Chriſt had cut a little ſtone out of that great monntaine, even a little ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill power out of Antichriſts great power; by vertue of this did Chriſt and his witneſſes looſe thoſe foure Angels out of this great river <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and being looſed, they preſently ſtand up with Chriſt and his Saints,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.16.</note> and open their mouthes and ſwallow up that flood which the Dragon caſt out of his mouth after the woman; yea, and they ſhall take part with Chriſt and his Army, and hate the Whore, and ſhall make her deſolate. At this time is noted in <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.2. and 8. that this little book was open in the hand of the Angel, which had been formerly ſhut and ſealed up; yea, this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel ſweares by him that liveth for evermore, that there ſhould be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121084:24"/>time no longer; that is, this myſtery of God ſhould now be fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and made plaine, that men may now ſee and underſtand what was contained within this little booke.</p>
               <p>This Seale and Trumpet agrees with the ſixth Viall,<note place="margin">The ſixth Viall pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red forth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.12.</note> and ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares to be one and the ſame, <hi>Which was poured upon that great river</hi> Euphrates, <hi>whereupon three ſpirits, like froggs, goe out of the mouth of the Dragon, and out of the mouth of the Beaſt, and out of the mouth of the falſe prophets,</hi> even the Devill and the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour and the Pope, and theſe are the ſpirit of Devils working miracles, Prieſts and Jeſuites, &amp;c. who go forth to the Kings of the Earth, to gather together many waters or people unto the battell of the great God Almighty, now upon this great river <hi>Euphrates;</hi> or many people doth Chriſt and his Saints, with the men of the Earth that help them poure forth the ſixth Viall, and ſo drieup this great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that way may be made for the Kings of the Eaſt; yea, that Chriſtian Kings and Princes may raigne upon the Earth. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond woe is paſt, and behold the third woe commeth quickly, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.14.</p>
               <p>The ſeventh Seale being opened, ſilence is in Heaven,<note place="margin">The ſeventh Seal is open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.1.</note> the high place of Judicature, for the ſpace of halfe an houre; ſee <hi>chap.</hi> 9. at this time <hi>is the Prayers of all Saints offered up to God upon the golden Altar which was before the throne in the Temple;</hi> that is, then ſhall the Churches of the Saints in and upon that golden Altar, Chriſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers up praiſes and thankſgiving unto God, for executing venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon his Enemies, and for the delivering of his Churches from bondage and miſery, which hath been the prayers of all Saints from the evening to the morning, 2300. yeares almoſt, and now will be fully anſwered at this time.</p>
               <p>This agrees with the voice of the ſeventh Trumpet, for when it ſounded, there was great voices heard in Heaven in the Church,<note place="margin">The ſeventh Trumpet ſounds. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15.</note> ſaying, the Kingdomes of this world are now become the Lords, and his Chriſts, and now Antichriſt is deſtroyed, and the powers of States is in the hands of Chriſt and his witneſſes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he and they ſhall raigne for ever and ever. Whereupon the Church, with her officers which ſit upon the Seates of their glory in Chriſts Houſe and Temple, fell upon their faces, noting thereby their owne humility and their high eſteeme of Chriſt, worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping him, and giving thanks to God Almighty, which was, is, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121084:25"/>is to come, becauſe he hath now taken to him his great power, and doth raigne.</p>
               <p>Which Seale and Trumpet argues with the ſeventh Viall which was poured upon that Antichriſtian aire,<note place="margin">The ſeventh Viall poured forth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.17, 18.</note> by the peaching of the Goſpel, which is to be done when the fifth and ſixth Viall is pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon the ſeate of the Beaſt, and that great <hi>River Euphrates; Even then came voices out of the Temple,</hi> which cauſeth a great ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall earth-quake amongſt thoſe antichriſtian men; that there ſhall be ſuch infinite ſtore of men converted to the faith, and brought home to Chriſt, as never was ſince men was upon the face of the Earth; and then ſhall an infinite company, as it were, be before the throne, ſinging <hi>Alleluiah,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Salvation, and glory, and honour, and power, be unto the Lord our God, for executing juſtice and judgement upon that great Whore.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.1, 2. and 6.</note> Yea, the voice of a great multitude, and the voice of many waters of many people, and of mighty thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſaying, <hi>Alleluiah,</hi> and the foure Beaſts and the twenty foure Elders fell downe and worſhipped God that ſate on the throne, ſaying,<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Amen, Alleluiah, verſ.</hi> 4. Thus the third woe is come upon that antichriſtian ſtate to her utter ruine and deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Thus we have ſeen the ſeven Seales, and the ſeven Trumpets, and ſeven Vials, to be all about one and the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>Firſt, ſealing up Gods judgements for a time; afterwards the Seales broke open, the Miniſters of the Churches by the preaching of the Goſpel declares what theſe judgements are, and then the Angels poured forth their Vials upon that Antichriſtian world.</p>
               <p>The next thing we are to doe in the following Chapters, is to ſhew what the fifth and ſixth and ſeventh Vials are more fully, and whom thoſe Angels be which are to poure them forth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:121084:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The firſt worke of the witneſſes after they are in Heaven, is chiefly the pouring forth of the fifth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iall, and the meanes whereby they doe it, with thoſe effects which follow upon it.</head>
               <p>THe witneſſes being aſcended up to Heaven, and Chriſt come in them, and ſate downe upon the throne to execute judgment upon Antichriſt;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.10 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.13.</note> the firſt thing we reade ſhall bee done is the pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring forth the fifth Viall, which is poured forth upon the throne and ſeate of the Beaſt. He is ſaid to have <hi>his throne above the Stars of God,</hi> above his Saints in his Temple, and likewiſe upon <hi>the Mount of the Congregation,</hi> the high place of Judicature; It hath appeared to all the world that hee hath taken all power into his hand, both Eccleſiaſticall and Civill; upon theſe powers muſt the witneſſes poure forth the fifth Viall; that is, they are to take all power from Antichriſt both in Church and State;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.26.9.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith <hi>Daniel, the judgement ſhall ſit, and they ſhall take away his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions:</hi> Againe, ſaith he, <hi>I beheld till the thrones were cast downe.</hi> And when Jeſus Chriſt ſate upon his throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.16. then every mountaine was moved out of his place, meaning the powers which Antichriſt had in the world. Now the meanes by which Chriſt and his witneſſes ſhall take theſe powers and dominions from An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, and ſo ſlay him as he did them, is by the power of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill ſword, as the Lord ſaith, <hi>He that leads into captivity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.10.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall go into captivity, be that kils with the Sword, ſhall be killed with the Sword.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Antichriſt by the power of the civill ſword, which he received from the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2.</note> did carry the people of God captive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wilderneſſe, for the ſpace of 1260. yeares, where they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied in ſack-cloath and afterwards civilly killed them, and laid them dead for three daies and a halfe. The like muſt the witneſſes do to Antichriſt, carry him captive, and civilly kill or ſlay him: this was that which the Saints of God beleeved long ſince, and with patience have they waited for it; therefore ſaith the Lord, <hi>This is the faith and patience of the Saints,</hi> the Saints beleeved it, and patiently did waite for it: By this power ſhall Chriſt and his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121084:26"/>
                  <hi>take the Kingdomes and Dominions</hi> from Antichriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.26. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.45.</note> 
                  <hi>and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume him to the end,</hi> which is ſet forth <hi>to be a little ſtone, cut out of the Mountaine without hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By Mountaine is not meant the Church, and by little ſtone Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.2.14.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.1. <hi>Mich.</hi> 4.1.</note> as ſome have ſuppoſed; but by mountaine is meant that great civill power which the foure great Beaſts, and little horne Anrichriſt had in the world, ſet forth by thoſe ten hornes. For by Mountaine or Mountaines, is meant power or powers; either the civill power of States and Kingdomes, of the Eccleſiaſticall power of Churches, uſually and frequently ſet forth by Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines. That great civill power which theſe great Beaſts had, is ſet forth by a Mountaine;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34, 35.</note> and there muſt be a little ſtone or little pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er cut out of this great power, that muſt <hi>ſmite this great Image</hi> of thoſe five Beaſts <hi>upon its feet, and break it all to peeces, and it ſhall become like the chaffe of the ſummer threſhing-floore, that no place ſhall be found for it And this little ſtone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall become a very great Mountaine, and fill the whole Earth;</hi> a little ſtone ſhall be cut out of this great moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine without hands; that is, a little civill power ſhall be cut out of that great civill power which Antichriſt had in all his ten Kingdomes, and this muſt be done without power of hands; not the power of an Hoaſt or Armes, but another way. And this wee ſee fulfilled before our eyes, in the yeare of Chriſt 1639. when the witneſſes aſcended up to Heaven, and the Lord Jeſus not only rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them from that dead ſtate and condition, and ſet them upon their feet, but tooke them up to the high place of Judicature, and by his Spirit hewed or cut a little power out of that great civill power which the <hi>Roman</hi> Beaſt and the little Horne had in all theſe ten Kingdomes: By which little power or ſtone the witneſſes in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and they here in <hi>England,</hi> have begun to break this Image and will go on in this and the other eight Kingdomes, till they have broken it all to peeces; and this little ſtone in their hands ſhall become a very great Mountaine, and fill the world very ſhortly.</p>
               <p>So yee ſee the meanes by which the Lord Chriſt and his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, ſhall take the Kingdomes and Dominions from Antichriſt, and conſume and deſtroy him to the end, even by the power of the civill ſword, ſo far as he hath ſeated and rooted himſelfe in the world; but as he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooted himſelfe in the hearts and mindes of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121084:26"/>men, by his curſed errors and hereſies,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Eev.</hi> 19.21. ☜</note> 
                  <hi>So the Lord will conſume him by the breath of his mouth, and brightneſſe of his comming;</hi> even by that ſpirituall ſword of the Goſpel, which ſword proceeds out of his mouth.</p>
               <p>The fifth Viall muſt be the firſt worke which Chriſt and his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſhall do after they are aſcended up to Heaven, and ſate upon their throne; and this they muſt do by that little ſtone cut out of the Mountaine, by that little civill power, put into their hands; which we ſee done the ſame time in which they aſcended to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in <hi>Scotland.</hi> Did not the godly party, by a ſolemn Oath taken before the moſt high God, caſt off Pope and Prelate, and all that whole Antichriſtian rabble out of Heaven, for having any more power, either in Church or State, but to be caſt out to the Earth? And this was done by vertue of that little civill power which they had as they ſate in the place of Judicature. This was evident before our eyes, 1639. done by the godly party in <hi>Scotland;</hi> and it was foretold to be ſo by the Spirit of propheſie:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13.</note> The ſame houre <hi>was there a great earthquake,</hi> a great ſhaking and feare amongſt the antichriſtian party, when the tenth part of the City fell.</p>
               <p>By City is not meant the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> but all thoſe ten King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes that are under the government of the Beaſt and his Image; and the tenth part is one of theſe ten Kingdomes, which was <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and this fell the ſame houre; and in this earthquake, when the tenth part fell, there was foure great effects or conſequences which followed upon it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, there was ſlaine of men ſeven thouſand,<note place="margin">Foure effects which follow upon the fall of the tenth part of that Antichriſtian City.</note> a certaine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſet down for an uncertaine; this ſlaying is not naturall but a civill ſlaying, a taking away all that power which they had in Church and State affaires; ſo it came to paſſe in <hi>Scotland</hi> at the ſame time when they caſt off the power of Antichriſt; there was civilly ſlaine a great number of Popiſh Lords and Prelates.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the ſecond effect is the ſounding of the ſeventh Trumpet, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. which was the preaching of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Effect <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes being in Heaven, gave leave to have the Goſpel preached, which was denyed by Antichriſt: at the ſounding of which Trumpet the Lord foretold, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.8. that then the myſtery of God which was revealed to his Prophets, and written in a little booke,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.9. <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.2, 3.</note> ſealed with ſeven Seales, faſt cloſed up till the end, is now finiſhed, and is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121084:27"/>to ſpeake and to be made plaine upon tables,<note place="margin">The ſeventh Trumpet is ſaid to ſound preſently up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up into Heaven, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they gave liberty to have the Goſpel prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, which is indeed the pouring forth of the ſeventh Viall.</note> that he that runs may reade it.</p>
               <p>Upon the ſeventh Trumpet ſounding and declaring what was now done in Heaven the high place of Judicature, preſently there was great voices of confidence and affiance in Heaven, the Church, that now the Kingdomes of this world ſhould be taken out of that wicked antichriſtian Beaſts hands, and given into the hands of Chriſt and his Saints. The people of God ſeeing Jeſus Chriſt and his witneſſes taking but the tenth part of the Kingdoms from Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, they looke from the beginning of the work to the end, and were confident that the time of the enemies ruine was now come, and the Churches ſinall deliverance, and the civill power of all the Kingdomes in the world ſhould be put into the hands of Chriſt and his Saints, and they ſhall raigne for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>The ſame thing was ſhewed to <hi>Daniel</hi> almoſt 2300. yeares ſince, when he ſaw the ancient of daies ſit, and the thrones of the Beaſt caſt downe:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9.13.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Then one like the Son of man came to the ancient of daies, and there was given him dominions and glory, and a Kingdome, that all people, nations, and languages, ſhould ſerve him; and not him only, but the Saints of the moſt High; and the Kingdomes and Dominions and the greatneſſe of the Kingdomes under the whole Heavens ſhall be given to the people of the Saints of the moſt high, and they ſhall poſſeſſe the Kingdome even for ever, ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Three terms and ſections of times ſhall the Saints poſſeſſe the Kingdoms of the world after Antichriſt hath his powers taken out of his hands, as we ſhall ſhew anon: The Churches of Chriſt do not only expreſſe their confidence and affiance they had in God for the accompliſhment of this great worke that was now begun,<note place="margin">Verſ. 16.</note> but they with all humility and reverence fall upon their faces before God, and worſhip him in giving him thanks and praiſe, <hi>which is, and was, and is to come, who hath taken to him his great power, and hath raigned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And they further declare, that the Nations of the antichriſtian world were angry,<note place="margin">Verſ. 18.</note> as indeed they were, at his great worke now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun; and that the time of his wrath againſt the wicked is now come, and the time of the dead that they ſhould now be judged, that is, that now judgment ſhall be given to the poore Saints of God, and witneſſes of Chriſt that were ſlaine, and lay dead for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121084:27"/>three daies and a halfe, and that he ſhould give a reward unto his ſervants the Prophets, and to the Saints, and to them that fear his Name, both ſmall and great; and ſhould deſtroy them that have deſtroyed the Earth, which the Lord will accompliſh in this preſent age.</p>
               <p>The third effect is the opening of the Temple by Chriſt and his witneſſes which ſate in Heaven,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Effect.</hi> 3. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Temple of God was opvned in Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By Temple is meant the Church the people of God: By Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is meant the high place of Judicature, ſo by the Temple of God; being opened in Heaven, is nothing elſe but Chriſt and his Witneſſes giving leave and liberty to the people of God thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregated to worſhip Chriſt in his Temple.</p>
               <p>And this they did, firſt, by their connivence and forbearing to trouble them and to moleſt them, as Antichriſt and his faction did, and afterwards they ſhall give them ſome liberty,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.12.</note> being tender over the conſciences of men in matters of worſhip.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.6.</note> But at the end of the ruine of Antichriſt, Then the Temple ſhall be ſet wide open, that whoſoever will ſhall enter in, if they be not ſuch as defile or work abomination. This we have ſeen fulfilled before our eyes, that thoſe that were Chriſts Witneſſes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.</note> they countenanced and ſpared to moleſt the people of God, that had joyned themſelves in League and Covenant to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 27.</note> and not to meddle at all with that Antichriſtian cup of ſpirituall fornications, and to worſhip their Lord and Husband Chriſt, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to divine inſtitution; but thoſe that were of Antichriſts ſide, though pretended otherwiſe, they would be ſtirring up the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people againſt them, untill they were caſt out of Heaven to the earth, even all thoſe popiſh affected ones.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When the Temple of God was thus opened, there was ſeene in his Temple the Arke of his Testament,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">verſe 19.</note> then the Lord Chriſt who is the Arke of Gods Teſtement, was ſeen to be in his Temple, in the midſt of thoſe people that before was looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as factious and ſeditious men, but the Temple being open they prove otherwiſe. And when the Antichriſtian party <hi>ſaw that Chriſt and his Witneſſes tooke part with theſe men, then there were Voyces and Thunderings, and Lightnings, and an Earthquake, and a great Haile,</hi> that is, then there was great ſtirs, combuſtions,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121084:28"/>hurliburlies, quakings, and feares amongſt the Antichriſtian party. And laſt of all, theſe grew to a great haile, or great ſtorme and war (as weſhall ſee anon) between the ſervants and Witneſſes of Chriſt, and thoſe that were for the Dragon and Antichriſt in Heaven.</p>
               <p>The fourth effect was <hi>A great wonder which appeared in Heaven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Effect <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>a Woman cloathed with the Sunne.</hi> By Woman is meant the Church of God, who is cloathed with the Sunne of righteouſneſſe, and which have her Officers in the midſt of her, officiating and emptying the golden Oyle out of themſelves into the boſome of the Church,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 4.12. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 1.6.20.</note> and are as a Crowne of gold unto her head, ſet forth by 12 Stars, after the Tribes of the children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and the Moon is under her feet; that is, under her feet are all ſublunary conentment and delight, ſhee contemning them with holy ſcorn &amp; deriſion, and being great with child, cryed travailing in birth, and pained to be delivered; that is, the people of God ſeeing Chriſt and ſome of his Saints and Witneſſes in Heaven, and many that were with them were againſt Chriſt, and for the Dragon: The Church hereupon is with child, as it were, and travailes in paine to have a godly Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſet up in the world, that thoſe which were in Heaven, the high place of Judicature, that was againſt Chriſt and his Government, might be caſt out, that ſo the Lord Chriſt that man-childe might in and by his Saints rule the nations with a rod of iron, and this they cryed and travailed in paine to God by humble and fervent prayers, and to his Witneſſes that ſate in Heaven by humble peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from the yeer of Chriſt 1639. to 1641.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">☞ </seg>
                  </label> Whereupon <hi>another Wonder appeares in Heaven, a great red Dragon, having ten Hornes and ſeven Crownes upon his heads, he ſtood ready to devoure this man-child ſo ſoone as it was borne.</hi> The devil and ſatan in the Roman Beaſt, and his Image the Pope, and they in and by thoſe popiſh Lords and Prelats ſtood ready to hinder this great deſigne and birth of the Church by all the power and ſtrength they could make, which were cleare and evident to all our ſights, 1641. when the people of God beſtirred themſelves both to God by prayer, and to the godly party in the Parliament, that thoſe popiſh Lords and Prelats might be caſt out:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.5.</note> Whereupon thoſe Petitions and prayers were heard of Chriſt and his Witneſſes, and ſo the Church did not onely bring forth the man-child or government, but it was likewiſe received up
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121084:28"/>to God and his Throne, into the high place of Judicature, and the Dragon and the Beaſt in thoſe popiſh Lords and Prelats were caſt out to the earth by a wonderfull and miraculous hand of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence.</p>
               <p>Theſe foure Effects have beene very evidently fulfilled and brought to paſſe before the eyes of all, from the time the Witneſſes firſt aſcended up to Heaven, 1639. in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the yeere 1641. when the Popiſh Prelats were caſt out of Heaven here in <hi>England.</hi> Some ſay that the Church travailed in birth 320. with <hi>Constantine,</hi> who was that man-child, and ſo he was taken up to Heaven, and then the Church fled into the Wilderneſſe. But that cannot be the meaning of the Text; for the Churches worke at that time, as the Spirit of God hath declared, was to beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to give teſtimony to that great truth of Chriſts kingly power in his Churches, and ſo to all other truth which.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3.</note> Antichriſt would afterward deny, all the time of their propheſie 1260. yeers: And as for <hi>Constantine,</hi> he was not to rule all nations with a rod of iron, this onely belonged to Jeſus Chriſt, and to his Saints,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.21.</note> who were to reigne with him; therefore this cannot be meant of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> nor of that time, but of this very time, which we may plainly ſee by thoſe things which have been done in our ſight; and for that 6. <hi>verſe chap.</hi> 12. of the woman fleeing into the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, is brought in as a ſeale to the propheſie, with the 15. <hi>verſe.</hi> For from the 7. <hi>verſe</hi> of <hi>chap.</hi> 11. to the end of the 12. <hi>chap.</hi> the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God ſets downe nothing but what was to come to paſſe in our time here amongſt us, from the day and yeer, 1635. when the Witneſſes were ſlaine, to the yeer 1641. when the warre fell out to be in. Heaven, between the Dragon and his Angels, and Chriſt and his Angels; onely thoſe two verſes 6. and 14. of the 12. chapter, of the Church fleeing into the Wilderneſſe, 375. And when this man-child was received up to Heaven, and the Dragon and his Angels caſt out of Heaven to the earth, here in <hi>England</hi> by Chriſt and his Witneſſes, was a ſecond degree of the pouring forth of the fifth Viall upon the Throne of the Beaſt; for this caſting him out of Heaven to the Earth, is a taking away all his power from him both Civill and Eccleſiaſticall in Church and State.</p>
               <p>Thus that proud <hi>Lucifer, Sonne of the morning,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.10.12.</note> is <hi>ſaid to be fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from Heaven, and to be cut downe to the ground, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121084:29"/>weake,</hi> like the common people of the earth, both in <hi>Scotland</hi> and here in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The ſixt Viall poured upon Antichriſt, with the way or meanes by which it is done, and the Instrument by whom it is poured forth, the Beaſt and the falſe prophet taken and caſt into a Lake of fire, with the ſilence in Heaven about the ſpace of halfe an houre.</head>
               <p>THe Churches of the Saints declaring to all the world, that the way to have all oppreſſion and tyranny removed, and to bring in all peace and tranquility was to have all thoſe that did formerly tyrannize over them caſt out of office and place of government, and let the Civill power be put into the hands of Chriſt and his Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, ſhee bringing forth this man-child into the world, is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received up to Heaven by Chriſt and his Witneſſes: the devil and his angels who ruled the world before is now caſt out of Heaven to the Earth. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">☞ </seg>
                  </label> Upon this followes warre between the Dragon and his angels, and <hi>Michael</hi> and his angels, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.7. The Dragon at the ſame time, by his taile drawes the third part of the Starres of Heaven after him, <hi>verſe</hi> 4. the devil will not fall from Heaven alone but he will draw ſome of the Starres with him.</p>
               <p>By Heaven is meant the place of judicature: by Starres is meant thoſe men that ſits in Parliament. And was not this evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent? did not the third part of the Parliament fall off at the ſame time, and was drawne after the Dragon, even with his taile the popiſh Lords and Prelats, who are his taile, to make warre with Chriſt and his Church.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.13, 14</note> 
                  <hi>There g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es at the ſame time three uncleane ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits like Frogges out of the mouth of the Dragon the devil, and out of the mouth of the Roman Beaſt, and out of the mouth of the falſe prophet the Pope, which are the ſpirits of devils working miracles.</hi> That is, thoſe Jeſuiticall ſpirits, which work with as much policy and craft, as though they did work miracles, and ſo deceive and delude men. Theſe goe forth to the Kings of the whole world, to gather them to the battell of the great God Almighty:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15.</note> ſo the devil is ſaid to caſt a flood out of his mouth after the woman the Church, which brought forth this
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121084:29"/>man-child, a flood of wicked and ungodly men, which he had gathered by thoſe three ſpirits, This hath bin partly fulfilled before our eyes: Did not thoſe Jeſuiticall ſpirits go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> up and downe to the Kings of the earth, <hi>France, Spaine,</hi> &amp;c. to gather them together in battell againſt the Witneſſes and the Church of God? when they ſaw that popiſh Lords and Prelats were caſt out of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 1641. who are ſtill at worke with the Kings of the earth, and will be untill the worke be done. Chriſt and his Witneſſes ſeeing this, preſently they prepare and make ready for to wage warre againſt Antichriſt: Therefore he is ſaid, <hi>in righteouſneſſe to judge and make warre, and ſhall breake them in pieces like a Potters Veſſell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.27. Sixth Viall poured our. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo the Dragon fought and his angels, and</hi> Michael <hi>and his Angels;</hi> but ſaith the holy Ghoſt, <hi>they prevailed not, neither was their place any more found in Heaven.</hi> Antichriſt ſhall not prevaile, though the warre be long and bloody; neither ſhall he get the power of Church or State any more into his hands, after it is once taken out.</p>
               <p>This warre which is in Heaven between the Dragon and his Angels; and the Lord Jeſus and his Witneſſes that ſit in Parliament;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.15.</note> is the pouring forth of the ſixth Viall, upon that great River <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates,</hi> which muſt be dryed up before that myſticall <hi>Babylon</hi> can be taken, as that old river <hi>Euphrates</hi> was before; literall <hi>Babylon</hi> could be taken by the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> as the Lord foretold by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> as yee ſhall ſee in <hi>Ieremy</hi> 50.38. ſo ſee 38. compared with <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.32. where you ſhall ſee the Lord threatning deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto literall <hi>Babylon,</hi> with the drying up of that great river <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates,</hi> by ſtopping up the paſſages, and by burning up the reedes thereof with fire, which were done by <hi>Darius,</hi> who tooke this City from the King of <hi>Babylon, Dan.</hi> 5.30, 31. ſo ſhall this myſticall river <hi>Euphrates</hi> be dryed up in a myſticall ſenſe.</p>
               <p>By this river is meant thoſe great multitudes of people that ſhall be gathered together into Armies, to deſtroy Chriſt and his Witneſſes, and to keep the Dragon, Beaſt, and falſe prophet in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, in their ſeate and throne. And they are ſaid <hi>to be gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into a place called</hi> Armageddon, <hi>by the Devil, the Beaſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>and the falſe prophet, and with them thoſe ten Kings which gave their power and ſtrength to the Beaſt;</hi> theſe ſhall all make war with the Lambe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.4.</note> and he ſhall make war with them, and will raiſe a great Army againſt them, who are ſaid to be <hi>called, and choſen, and faithfull.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:121084:30"/>
               <p>The called ones are the men of the earth, who are ſaid to help Chriſt and his Church;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.16.</note> 
                  <hi>and the ten hornes which were upon the Beaſts head, are to hate the Where, and make her deſolate and naked, and ſhall eate her fleſh, and burne her with fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe hornes is meant the Commons of all thoſe ten King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, which were under the government of the Beaſt, in whom the power of States originally lies; and theſe ſhall be with the Lambe, and take part with him againſt the Beaſt, as we ſee <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> hath done already, and ſo will the commons of all the other eight Kingdomes doe, for the Word of God muſt be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. But thoſe ten Kings that were heads of thoſe ten States they ſhall take part with the Dragon, and make warre with Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by choſen are meant the Saints of the moſt High, who are ſaid to overcome Antichriſt.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſtly,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.11.</note> 
                     <hi>By the blood of the Lambe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, <hi>By the word of their teſtimony.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And laſt of all, <hi>They loved not their lives unto death.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">☞ </seg>
                  </label> They willingly ingaged themſelves in this great quarrell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt and the Beaſt. Choſen ones will be faithfull, (but not the called,) choſen and faithfull.</p>
               <p>The Lord Chriſt notes this of them that are choſen, that they ſhall be faithfull to him in this war, but yet he ſecretly hints to us, that the men of the earth will be trecherous: This great Army of Chriſt ſhall be raiſed by that little ſtone cut out of the Mountaine without hands, by that civill power which Chriſt and his witneſſes hath in their hands now they ſit in Heaven; therefore <hi>Heaven is ſaid to be opened;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11.</note> that is, now there is liberty given by them that ſit in Heaven. That now men ſhall take up armes againſt Antichriſt: The Lord Chriſt is upon a white Horſe in Heaven, as the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Lords Army;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5.14.</note> and the Armies which followes him, is ſaid to be in Heaven, being raiſed by that civill power which the witneſſes have in their hand in Heaven; and Chriſt and his Army is ſaid to be upon white Horſes, which note the innocency of the cauſe, and victory over them in this quarrell; it being the cuſtome of the Romans to ride in triumph after victory, upon white horſes, or elſe their Horſes and Chariots covered with white.</p>
               <p>Againe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.4.</note> the Lord Chriſt is ſaid to ſtand upon his feet upon the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121084:30"/>Mount of <hi>Olives,</hi> in the day he goes out to fight againſt thoſe Kings that carried the Church and people of God captive; which is meant of this very time.</p>
               <p>By Mount is meant power, and there be but two powers in the world, the Church power and the State power: It is not meant the Church power, for then this mount ſhould have been called Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> by which the Church power is alwaies ſet forth; and this Mount ſhould have been in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in the Church, and not before the Church. But this Mount is that civill power of States ſet forth by that Mount <hi>Olives</hi> which is before <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> ſo this civill power is before the Church of God, and chiefly for the good of the Church. And upon this Mount or power doth Chriſt ſtand with his feet. By feet he meanes his Saints, ſo the Lord Chriſt by his Spirit in his Saints and witneſſes, ſtands this day upon this Mount <hi>Olives. And this mount</hi> (ſaith the Text,) <hi>ſhall cleave in the midſt, towards the Eaſt, and towards the Weſt, towards the North, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the South.</hi> This is fulfilled at this day; Is not this power or Mount cloven in the middle? part of it is in the hands of Chriſt and his Witneſſes, as they ſit in Heaven, and part of it in the hands of Chriſt and his Army, which is in Heaven upon white Horſes. And this power ſhall extend it ſelfe from Weſt to Eaſt, from North to South, to take away the power from Antichriſt in all his ten Kingdomes, and to dry up that great river <hi>Euphrates</hi> from one end of the world to another; and this power or Mount is to be divided one part in the high place of Judicature, and the other part in the Armies, as is at this day, untill they have poured forth the fifth and ſixth Viall, and then it ſhall cloſe and become one, in the yeare of Chriſt 1655. So by that little ſtone, even that little civill power which is in the hands of the Witneſſes, ſhall the fifth and ſixth Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all be poured upon the Beaſt and that great River <hi>Euphrates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſixth Viall of Gods wrath and indignation,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34.2.</note> is ſaid to be poured upon. <hi>Euphrates, upon all Nations, and his fury upon all their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> upon all the ten Nations of Antichriſt, and upon all their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that ſhall be raiſed; <hi>be will utterly destroy them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>and give them up to the ſlaughter. The ſword of the Lord ſhall be bathed in Heaven, upon the high one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which are on high,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.21.</note> 
                  <hi>upon the Kings of the Earth upon the Earth; it ſhall be filled with blood,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.18.</note> 
                  <hi>that the Mountains ſhall be melted with their blood.</hi> This is called the overflowing ſcourge, which was to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121084:31"/>paſſe over the whole earth; and the houre of temptation that ſhould come upon all the world to try them;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.17, 18.</note> and the ſlaine ſhall be ſo many, <hi>that it is called the ſupper of the great God, and all the fowles of Heaven are to eate the fleſh of Kings, of Captaines, of mighty men, of the fleſh of horſes, and them that ſit on them, and the fleſh of all men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.18.</note> 
                  <hi>ſmall and great, bond and free;</hi> Even the third part of men that are upon the Earth ſhall be ſlaine in this warre, to dry up this great river <hi>Euphrates;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.12.</note> that a man of that Antichriſtian and myſticall <hi>Babylon; ſhall be more precious then fine gold, even a man, then the golden wedge of Ophir.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.11.</note> 
                  <hi>For by fire, and by ſword, will the Lord plead with all fleſh, and the ſlaine of the Lord ſhall be many,</hi> Iſa. 66.16. In this war the <hi>Roman</hi> Beaſt ſhall be taken and ſlaine, and his body given to the burning flames, and with him the falſe prophet that wrought mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles before him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20.</note> with which he deceived them that had received the marke of the Beaſt. <hi>Theſe both are cast alive into a lake, burning with fire and brimstone, this is the purpoſe which is purpoſed upon the whole earth, and this is the hand that is, and ſhall be ſtretched out upon all Nations, for the Lord of Hoſts hath purpoſed, and who ſhall diſanull it, and his hand is ſtretched out, and who ſhall turne it back, Iſa.</hi> 14.26, 27.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee the fifth and ſixth Viall poured upon the ſeat of the Beaſt, and upon that great river <hi>Euphrates;</hi> all his powers and ſtrength taken from him in heaven, himſelf caſt down to the earth, yea to hell, and his armies utterly deſtroyed and given to the beaſts of the field and to the fowles of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Yet there is another Viall to be poured out, namely, upon the aire, wherein Antichriſt breathed; but when the Witneſſes, Chriſts civill Magiſtrates that ſit in Heaven, have done that worke which is proper for them, as they are civill Magiſtrates; they ſhall ſit ſtill and keep ſilence in Heaven about the ſpace of halfe an houre, which is the full time that the ſeventh Viall ſhall be pouring forth, though the Beaſts have their Dominions taken from them. Yea, both the Beaſt and falſe prophet are caſt into a lake burning with fire and brimſtone;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.12.</note> yet theſe are ſaid to live ſtill in the hearts of thoſe men, in whom thoſe errors and hereſies do ſtill abide, which they brought into the world by their Antichriſtian aire; and this remnant of men are not to be deſtroyed by the power of the civill Sword;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.21.</note> but to be deſtroyed by a myſticall and ſpirituall ſword, which proceeded out of the mouth of him that ſits upon the white
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121084:31"/>Horſe, and by ſpirituall men ſent out of the Temple,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.17.</note> therefore the civill Magiſtrate ſhall keepe ſilence all the ſame time, even about the ſpace of halfe an houre, and ſit and reſt themſelves, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving done the beſt worke that ever was done before them, or that ſhall be done after them.</p>
               <p>We cannot ſuppoſe this ſilence to be in Heaven ſtrictly for half an houre; no, nor half a day, moneth, or yeare; for the ſeventh Viall muſt be poured forth upon that Antichriſtian aire, all the ten Kingdomes over; in this ſpace of time that this ſilence is to be in Heaven, which cannot be in ſo ſhort a time, neither can it be meant of any longe time,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.32.</note> becauſe Antichriſt muſt be deſtroyed in one age and generation of men, Chriſt ſpeaking of the ruine of Antichriſt myſtically, as well as of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> literally: therefore we are to take this ſilence for the ſpace of half an houre, for the ſpace of 45. yeares, in which time the ſeventh Viall is pouring forth, as ſhall appeare more fully when we come to ſpeake of the time or times of the ending of theſe Vials.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, that this ſilence was in Heaven when the ſeventh Seale was opened; this we are to note, that it was the cuſtome of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> to write thoſe things that were of greater conſequence in ſheets of parchment, and ſo to roll them up, and ſeale them if they were things ſecret. The Spirit of God alluding to this their cuſtome, ſets forth to us, that every Viall was written in a roll of parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and every roll was ſealed, ſeven Vials were written in ſeven rolls, and every roll had a ſeale; and when the firſt Viall was to be poured forth, then the firſt ſeal was broken open, and the firſt trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſounded.</p>
               <p>The Seale was broken open, that men might ſee what was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the roll: and the trumpet, which was the Goſpel in the mouth of the Miniſters of the Churches, was to declare to that Antichriſtian world, what the Judgement or the Viall was, which God was then pouring forth upon them; and the Viall or Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that they were to feel with paine and anguiſh, when the Lord poured it forth.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">☜ </seg>
                  </label> So when the firſt Viall was poured forth, the firſt Seal was open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the firſt Trumpet ſounded, and ſo in order the ſecond and third, unto the ſeventh.</p>
               <p>And when the ſeventh Seale was opened, the ſeventh Viall was poured forth, and then this ſilence was in Heaven.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:121084:32"/>
               <p>Before we leave ſpeaking of the ſixth Viall, we are to take notice of this; that although the Lord be come in the clouds of our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, even in his Witneſſes ſtanding upon the Mount Olives, and the judgement ſeat, and the Thrones are caſting downe, yea, and the Lord is gone out to fight and make warre with thoſe Kings that carried the Church of God captive, and himſelfe upon the white horſe, and much of the worke is done; yet at this time, the holy Ghoſt ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.28.</note> 
                  <hi>That the light ſhall not be cleare no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> darke, the morning Star is but newly riſen, and a very little light doth yet appeare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is ſo much darkneſſe, as very few of the Saints themſelves doe not ſee nor know what the Lord Chriſt is doing, either for Churches or States; great feares amongſt moſt of the Saints, that ſorrow and miſery will come to both: They cannot as yet ſee how or when the Church of Chriſt ſhall be delivered, nor the pure way of Chriſts worſhip in his Houſe and Temple ſet up; <hi>onely a few choyce ones that be wiſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3.</note> 
                  <hi>and they ſhall ſhine as the brightneſſe of the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> That is, thoſe godly ones whom the Lord hath made wiſe to underſtand the Myſtery of pure Ordinances of worſhip, and the way and Government of Chriſt in his Houſe and Temple, at this time wherein the worſhip of God is ſo exceedingly corrupted and pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the abominations of that Babyloniſh Whore, they ſhall ſhine in this Antichriſtian world as the brightneſſe of the Firmament, for the preſent; <hi>And they that turne many to righteouſneſſe as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When they ſhall not onely ſee and be able to diſcerne between gold and droſſe, water and pure wine; Chriſts owne inſtitutions and mens inventions, and the falſe government of Antichriſt, and the true government of Chriſt in and over his Church and people; but alſo turne many unto thoſe righteous and pure Ordinances of worſhip, <hi>even they</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>ſhall ſhine as Starres,</hi> not in this age and time onely, <hi>but for ever and ever, their names ſhall be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, unto all the Churches of the Saints.</hi> For the firſt ever or terme of time which Chriſt and his Saints ſhall reigne, in peace even a 1000. yerres. And for ever to the ſecond terme or end of time; after the 1000. yeares are ended from the deſtruction of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> unto the end of the world, becauſe they were ſo wiſe to ſee, and diligent and faithfull to turne many unto the right way of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:121084:32"/>
               <p>But there is ſome light, though it be not cleard, ſo that thoſe which are ſaid to be wiſe, can ſee and underſtand in part, that now the day-ſtarre is riſen, and the great work concerning the enemies ruine, and the Saints finall deliverance is begun, and the Sunne of righteouſneſſe, the Lord Chriſt, will ere long ariſe with healing in his Wings.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Maal.</hi> 4.2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But at this time it is not light nor darke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>a day as it were knowne to the Lord, onely,</hi> none elſe knowing or underſtanding what God is doing for his people, onely a few whom he hath made wiſe to underſtand a viſion, the words of the wiſe God concerning this great Myſtery, and the darke ſayings thereof.</p>
               <p>Againe, this is noted, <hi>that it is not day nor night:</hi> The day of the Churches peace is not yet come, nor the night of her miſery and bondage is not fully upon her as it hath been, but ſhee is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the day and night (in the birth) and upon the borders of ſpirituall <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But at the even-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ide,</hi> when the worke ſhall be almoſt at an end,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.7.</note> then it ſhall be day-light, all ſhall ſee what God is doing for his Church, and then will that glorious Sunne ſhine forth in his full brightneſſe and glory, that the light of the Moone ſhall be as the Sunne, and the Sunne ſeven-fold, then the eyes of the blind ſhall be opened to ſee the way of Chriſt in his Houſe ſo plainly, that way faring men, though fooles, ſhall not erre therein.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.8, <hi>&amp;</hi> 6</note>
               </p>
               <p>And this is alſo noted in the Scripture of truth, that an Army out of the North ſhall come up againſt <hi>Babyon,</hi> and be the chiefe cauſe of her mine and deſtruction: <hi>They come from a farre Country, from the end of Heaven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.5.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord and the Weapons of his indignation to destroy the whole Land:</hi> which is meant of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> For we are a very remote Country from myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> from the end of Heaven as <hi>Scotland</hi> is; yea, if we look to the men that are to be imployed in this warre, we ſhall ſee them to be the ſame which the Lord Chriſt hath in his Army at this day, as we may ſee in the third verſe: <hi>I have commanded my ſanctified ones,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 3.</note> 
                  <hi>I have alſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led my mighty ones for my anger, even them that rejoyce in my highneſſe:</hi> The Lord meaning his owne ſervants, who are ſaid to retoyce in his highneſſe, aud are ſet forth by choſen and faithfull ones, which are now with the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.14. following him upon white horſes in Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.14. who are this day upon the high places
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121084:33"/>of the field, and are ſaid to be in Heaven with their Army, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are raiſed by Chriſt and his Witneſſes, who are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and by that ciuill power which they have in their hands by right, as they are lawfully called to that high place.</p>
               <p>Againe, wee ſhall ſee that the Lord intended <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to come againſt this myſticall <hi>Babylon,</hi> if wee looke in <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> 50.9. <hi>I will raiſe and cauſe to come up againſt</hi> Babylon <hi>an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of great Nations, from the North Countrey.</hi> Now of all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries in the World, <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> is North to myſticall <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And againe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.44.</note> 
                  <hi>Tydings out of the Eaſt, and out of the North, ſhall trouble him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By Eaſt, here ſurely (as may be ſuppoſed) is meant the <hi>Sweedes.</hi> And by North is meant <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> ſo conſequently they ſhall joine together againſt Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Rut all theſe threatnings were againſt literall Babylon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I grant they were in the Letter, but as truly as <hi>Rome</hi> is called my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall <hi>Babylon;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5.</note> and as truly as all theſe threatnings which the Lord hath pronounced againſt literall <hi>Babylon,</hi> were made good in the Letter againſt them; ſo will the Lord do againſt myſticall <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> in a ſpirituall and myſticall way: Therefore when <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> have dryed up the River <hi>Euphrates</hi> here, they ſhall not then ſit downe on this ſide <hi>Jordan,</hi> to enjoy peace themſelves, and leave their brethren in miſery beyond the Sea, and out of their owne poſſeſſions, but ſhall go over <hi>Jordan</hi> with a ſtrong Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, to help their Brethren, that they may likewiſe dry up that Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Euphrates</hi> there, to the utter ruine of Antichriſt, and for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a perfect peace in the ten States, that the powers of States and Churches may be put into the hands of Chriſt and his Saints, that they may live and raigne over the Nations of the earth in peace and tranquility 1000. yeaees.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:121084:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> The ſeventh Viall poured forth; two great effects follow thereupon: The firſt is the hringing in the fullneſſe of the Gentiles. And the ſecond is the calling of the Jewes, with the time when the fifth, ſixth, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Viall began and ended, and liberty given to the Saints by the Witneſſes, to build that new <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe fifth and ſixth Viall being poured upon Antichriſts ſeate and thrones, and upon his Armies, the Beaſt and falſe prophet taken by Chriſt and his Army that followed him upon white Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Heaven, <hi>and both of them caſt into a lake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.21.</note> 
                  <hi>hurning with fire and brimſtone.</hi> Yet there is a remnant of that Antichriſtian race left, whom Antichriſt hath poyſoned with his Antichriſtian aire, with errors and hereſies, in whom thoſe five Beaſts are ſaid to live,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.12.</note> though they be dead: Therefore the Lord Jeſus hath another Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to poure upon theſe men, as is the maladie, ſuch is the medicine;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.10.</note> and as the diſeaſe, ſo is the cure. The diſeaſe is inward in their ſpirits, their underſtanding is filled with miſts and darkneſſe which Antichriſt brought into the world, with which he filled his whole Kingdome.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This Vial muſt be poured upon this Antichriſtian aire and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by the preaching of the Goſpell. For this being an inward and ſpirituall worke, is fitteſt for ſpirituall weapons and ſpirituall men, and ſuch will Chriſt have to do the worke,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Therefore voices came forth of the Temple:</hi> The Miniſters of the Churches are to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in this worke, and ſpirituall weapons or ſwords, therefore ſaith the Scripture, <hi>The remnant were ſlaine by the ſword of him that ſate upon the white horſe, which ſword proceedeth out of his mouth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.21.</note> The way of Antichriſt hath been to ſlay ſuch men, (as they conceive factious and erronious,) with the civill ſword;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.12.</note> therefore he gets an Hoſt, or the power of Princes,<note place="margin">The civill ſword uſed by Antichriſt to root errors out of mens hearts.</note> and hales them before Princes and Judges for to root out errors, (as they pretend) out of their mindes; but this is a prepoſterous way, they may ſooner root their hearts out of their breſts. But we ſee Chriſts way, he uſeth the Civill Sword to take away all Antichriſts power, which he got by
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121084:34"/>the Civill Sword,<note place="margin">Chriſt uſeth a ſpirituall ſword to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move and caſt out all thoſe errors that are in mens ſpirits.</note> and ſo ſlays him, carry him captive, and likewiſe dry up that River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> but ſpiritually to ſlay men, in remove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing darkneſſe and ignorance out of their underſtanding, and ſo conſequently errors and hereſies, he hath a ſpirituall Sword fit for the worke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So the ſeventh Angel poured forth the ſeventh Viall into the aire, and then came a great voice out of the Temple of Heaven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>from the Throne, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, It is done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By aire is meant that Antichriſtian ignorance and darkneſſe wherewith Antichriſt had filled the whole world.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6.7.</note> By voices is meant the Goſpel. By Temple is meant the Church or Churches of the Saints, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. This voice came out of the Temple, that is, the Churches of the Saints ſent forth Meſſengers or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to preach the Goſpel,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6.</note> 
                  <hi>to every Nation, kinred, tongue, and people.</hi> The Temple of Heaven from the civill throne, Chriſt and his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes being in Heaven, the high place of Judicature, where they have their throne; the Spirit of God joines the Temple and this Heaven together, and Chriſts civill Magiſtrates and his Churches go hand in hand, and with joint conſent ſend forth Miniſters to preach the Goſpel;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6.</note> therefore it is ſaid, <hi>I ſaw an Angel flee through the midſt of Heaven, having the everlaſting Goſpel to preach, &amp;c. ſaying, It is done.</hi> Theſe Miniſters ſhall declare to all the world, that now the worke is done; the Kingdomes and Dominions are taken from the Beaſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.11, 12.</note> and their bodies given to the burning flame, and their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mles utterly deſtroyed, and given up to the ſlaughter, and ſo the worke is as good as done;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34.2.</note> And another ſhall come after them, and ſay,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Babylon is fallen, Babylon is fallen:</hi> And another after him ſhall come and pronounce the judgments of God againſt every man that retains and holds faſt thoſe Antichriſtian errors,<note place="margin">Verſ. 9, 10.</note> ſaying; <hi>If any man worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and receive his marke in their hands, or in their foreheads, the ſame man ſhall drinke of the wine of the wrath of God, which is poured out without mixture into the cup of his indignation, and he ſhall be tormented with fire and brimſtone, in the preſence of the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and in the preſence of the Lambe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this great voice of the Goſpel ſhall follow two great ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects or conſequences:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, the bringing in of the fulneſſe of the Gentiles.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, the calling home of the Jewes.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:121084:34"/>
               <p>Firſt, the fulneſſe of the Gentiles ſhall come in, declared in theſe words, <hi>That there were voices, and thundering and lightning,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.18.</note> 
                  <hi>and there was a great earthquake.</hi> By voices, lightning, &amp;c. is meant great ſtirs and combuſtions amongſt men, not in a warlike way, as were before, but in diſputing and arguing about matters of Religion. And by earthquake is meant a great falling off and renouncing thoſe Antichriſtian tenets and errors, which they formerly held, to imbrace the ſincere truths of the Goſpel, both for Doctrine and Diſcipline, which is called the bringing in of the fulneſſe of the Gentiles. And this earthquake ſhall be ſo mighty and ſo great, <hi>as was not the like ſince men lived on the earth,</hi> there will be ſuch a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall falling off and renouncing of their errors,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.25.</note> and ſuch a true and thorow imbracing of the truths of the Goſpel, as never was ſince men were upon the earth; this is called the firſt reſurection.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And this great City is ſaid to be divided into three parts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.19.</note> one part is to be ſlaine civilly, to have all their civill power taken from them, as thoſe ſeven thouſand were ſlaine in <hi>Scotland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13.</note> at the fall of the tenth part of the City, by Chriſt and his witneſſes that ſit in Heaven.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Another part is to be ſlaine by the naturall ſword,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. and 14.</note> 
                  <hi>by him that ſits upon the white Horſe, and they which follow him upon white Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Heaven;</hi> upon the high places of the field, in his Army.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The third part is to be ſlaine ſpiritually, by that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſword of the Goſpel, <hi>which proceedeth out of the mouth of Chriſt,</hi> which is that voice that came out of the Temple. So this great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is divided into three parts,<note place="margin">Verſ. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>and thus great Babylon is ſaid to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to remembrance before God, and to drinke of the cup of the wine of the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his wrath and fury.</hi> Thus will the Lord deal with <hi>Babylon,</hi> even deal with her as ſhe did with the Saints; yea, reward her double,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6.</note> ſhe brake the Saints to peeces, ſo ſhall ſhe be broken to peeces like a Potters Veſſell, that ſhall not be ſet together againe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.27.</note> ſhe devoured the Saints, ſo ſhall ſhe be devoured; <hi>Every man that is found of her ſhall be thrust through, and every one that is joyned to her,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.15.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall fall by the ſword.</hi> She ſlew the Saints by a civill ſword, and tooke away all their powers from them, and led them into captivity, ſo ſhall ſhe be ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy ſlaine by the ſame Sword and carried captive,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.10.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſhut up as priſoners in a pit, and civilly bound for many yeares.</hi> They laid the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes dead bodies in the ſtreets of that ſpirituall <hi>Sodome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.22.</note> ſo ſhall they lye dead and bound with Satan a thouſand yeares,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.3, 5.</note> not put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121084:35"/>their graves;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.19.</note> nay worſe, <hi>they ſhall be caſt out of their graves, like on abominable branch,</hi> loathſome and vile for all men to behold, <hi>even as the rayment of him that is thruſt through with a Sword, and as a carkaſſe trodden under foot; thus ſhall it be done to myſticall Babylon, the mother of Haroots,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5. rindx;</note> 
                  <hi>and the abominations of the whole earth; the zeale of the Lord of Hoſt will do all this in his appointed time:</hi> And the Lord gives the reaſon of all this his fury,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 37.32.</note> and wrath, and indignation, againſt <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon;</hi> and ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34.8.</note> 
                  <hi>It is the day of the Lords vengeance, the yeare of recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences for the controverſie of</hi> Zion, <hi>and it is the vengeance of the Lord, even the vengeance of his Temple;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.28.</note> 
                  <hi>the violence done to me and to my fleſh, be upon</hi> Babylon, <hi>ſhall the Inhabitants of</hi> Zion <hi>ſay, and my blood upon the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of</hi> Chaldea,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.35.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>ſay: Thus will the Lord pleade his Churches cauſe, and take vengeance for her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond great effect which followes upon the ſeventh Vials pouring forth, is the calling of the Jewes, <hi>The Lord ſhall ſet his hand again the ſecond time to recover</hi> Iſrael:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.11.</note> When the Jews ſhall ſee the utter ruine of the Romiſh Beaſt, and his Image the Pope, with the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of all his Images and Idols. And likewiſe the extirpation of all that curſed tradition and invention, which Antichriſt is ſaid to bring into the world with him by his power, which are ſaid to be (666.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here is wiſdome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.18.</note> 
                  <hi>let him that hath underſtanding, count the number of the Beaſt, for it is the number of a man, and his number is</hi> (666.) That is, he that hath wiſdome to diſtinguiſh between thoſe traditions which that Antichriſtian Beaſt brought into the world, and mixed his cup with, and thoſe pure Ordinances of Worſhip, which he tooke from Chriſt and his Saints, in the day he entred into the Temple, let him but divide between the one and the other, and he ſhall finde thoſe traditions to be (666.)</p>
               <p>And when all theſe abominations are caſt out of the worſhip and ſervice of Chriſt, and they likewiſe heare thoſe bleſſed voices of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25, 26. <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.37. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.25.</note> which came out of the Temple; and likewiſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſame voices of the Goſpel, declaring the truth of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made to their fathers of old, and Gods free grace and love, and mercy in Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall thereby be brought into the bond of the Covenant; for ſaith the Text, <hi>blindneſſe happened unto the Jewes, but untill the fulneſſe of the Gentiles came in, and then all</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:121084:35"/>
               <p>Here we have, firſt, the meanes of their calling; ſecondly, the manner of it; thirdly, the effects of it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the meanes or way by which they ſhall be called, <hi>is by the ſound of the Trumpet of the Goſpel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.31.</note> 
                  <hi>and he ſhall ſend his Angels with a great ſound of a Trumpet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.12.</note> 
                  <hi>and they ſhall gather together his Elect</hi> (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Jewes) from the foure windes, from one end of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens to another.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the manner of their callings; <hi>Then ſhall the Lord poure upon them his ſpirit of humiliation and godly ſorrow, that they ſhall looke upon him whom they pierced, and ſhall mourne bitterly as one that mourneth for his onely Sonne, yea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10.</note> 
                  <hi>as the mourning of</hi> Hadda-drimmon <hi>in the Valley of</hi> Megiddon, <hi>which was the greateſt mourning that ever we read of</hi> Again,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.9.</note> 
                  <hi>with weeping and ſupplication will I lead them.</hi> Thus then the manner of it ſhall be with much ſorrow, lamentation and humilation.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the effects which follow upon this their great humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and converſion is, they ſhall enquire after the true Church-way of the Goſpell, which way the Lord Chriſt will be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in his Houſe and Temple, <hi>asking the way to Sion, with their faces thitherwards:</hi> which notes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.6.</note> that their hearts ſhall be fully ſet to worſhip Chriſt after his owne way, and it notes likewiſe their wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe and readineſſe to the worke, but yet not all of them ſhall God take into his Houſe and Temple; no, <hi>but one of a City,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and two of a Family, and bring them to Sion his Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>But all of them ſhall have their owne.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.25.20.42.34.13.24.</note> 
                  <hi>I and given them again for an everlasting poſſeſſion, and they ſhall dwell in it for ever, and none ſhall make them afraid, and they ſhall be no more a prey to the Heathen.</hi> Againe, <hi>I will bring againe the captivity of my people Iſrael, and they ſhall build the waſte places, and plant Vineyards and drinke the Wine thereof,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.14, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>and make Gardens and eat the fruit thereof, and I will plant them upon their owne Land, and they ſhall be no more pulled up out of the Land which I have given them, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Now the Jewes being ſcattered to the foure winds of Heaven amongſt all the people in the world, therefore this is noted of them, that they amongſt whom they lived in all Nations <hi>ſhall bring them to their owne Land upon horſes and in Chariots, and in Litters, and upon Mules, and upon ſwift Beasts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.20.</note> 
                  <hi>for an Offering to the Lord, to his holy Mountaine</hi> Jeruſalem. Gods Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in an outward way, is with all the naturall ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to bring them all into their own Land, <hi>and to give it them for an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121084:36"/>poſſeſſion; and they ſhall no more be two Nations, nor divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two Kingdomes any more,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.22.24.25. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>even the Lord Chriſt ſhall be King over them for ever,</hi> as he ſits King over Nations: But that Sion and Church-Covenant ſhall be but with ſome of them. By which Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, God is ſaid to be married to them: Therefore ſaith the Lord;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14.</note> 
                  <hi>I will take you one of a City, and two of a Family, and bring you to</hi> Sion, my Church and Temple: For we are not to ſuppoſe that the whole Nation of the Jewes, from Generation to Generation, for ſo many hundred yeares, will be all godly men and women; no, but all indeed ſhall ſubmit to that outward way of worſhip as other Kingdomes ſhall,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.16.</note> 
                  <hi>over whom Chriſt in his Saints ſhall reigne a thouſand yeares:</hi> But not all godly and holy men and women fit to be taken to <hi>Sion</hi> into that new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and holy City,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.1.</note> where God and the Lambe hath their ſpirituall Throne: Therefore ſaith the Lord to <hi>Daniel, All thy people ſhall be delivered,</hi> that is, with an outward deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from that captivity and ſlavery that wicked men kept them it;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>But ſome of them ſhall awake to everlasting life, and ſome to everlasting ſhame and contempt.</hi> Now we are to ſpeake of the time of the pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring forth of theſe three laſt Vials, and the end of Antichriſt; with the finall deliverance of the Churches from their captivity, and the beginning of that glorious reigne of Chriſt and his Saints, for a thouſand yeares; the time of the little horne, Antichriſt, and the laſt enemy of the Church: we have it ſet downe in <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. by a three-fold gradation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Question being put by one,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.6.</note> 
                  <hi>to the man cloathed in linen, How long it ſhould be to the end of thoſe wonders; after a ſolemne Oath taken by him that lives for ever.</hi> Which Oath notes the certainty and infallibility of the thing he ſware to, he gives a three-fold anſwer. Firſt, <hi>That it ſhould be for a Time,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Times, and halfe a Time.</hi> Secondly, a thouſand two hundred and ninety dayes. Thirdly, a thouſand three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and five and thirty dayes,</p>
               <p>The firſt, is the full time of Antichriſts reigne, in which he was to ſcatter the Churches power,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.7.</note> called <hi>the power of the holy people.</hi> Which power he ſcattered from the time of his beginning to reigne (not ſo much over the Empire) as over the Saints, to the end of his reigne, from the yeare 375. to the yeare 1635. the full time of 1260. yeares,<note place="margin">vid. chap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> which is a Time, Times, and halfe a Time, ſee the third Chapter. At which time then almoſt all his cruelty againſt the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121084:36"/>Saints ſhall be finiſhed, for he did to this very yeare ſlay the Saints, and laid them dead, and triumphs over them, and make merry, ſending gifts one to another; and at this time Antichriſt is ſaid to finiſh his reigne over the Saints having ſlaine them: and ſo is one time of his end come.</p>
               <p>Second time of his end, <hi>is</hi> 1290. <hi>dayes, which time begins,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>when thn daily Sacrifice was taken away, and that abomination ſet up, which made all deſolate.</hi> Which was done in the yeare of Chriſt 365. now 365. and 1290. are 1655. which is the ſecond time of his end, which is the end of the fifth and ſixth Viall pouring forth,<note place="margin">Carion. <hi>Chro. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.17, 18. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.11.</note> when all Civill and Eccleſiaſticall power ſhall be taken from him, <hi>and his Armies destroyed and given to the Fowles of Heaven, and their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to the burning flames.</hi> And all the civill power of States put into the hands of the godly, but not the Eccleſiaſticall power, untill the ſeven plagues of the ſeven Angels be fulfilled.</p>
               <p>The third time of his end is ſet down in the 12. verſe, to be 1335. <hi>dayes.</hi> By dayes, he means propheticall dayes, a day for a yeare, This time is to begin when the 1290. began, at the yeare 365. ſo 365. and 1355. make 1700. which is the third and laſt time of his end, when he ſhall be ſpiritually ſlain and caſt out of the hearts &amp; minds of men, in whom he hath faſtly rooted himſelf by his Antichriſtian errours;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.12.</note> in whom he and the reſt of the Beaſt was ſaid to live af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had their Dominions and Kingdomes taken from them.</p>
               <p>At this time the Lord Chriſt is ſaid to ſit upon the Throne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.1, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and much people in Heaven crying Alleluiah; and the voyce of a great Multitude, and as the voyces of many waters, and the voyce of mighty thunderings, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Alleluiah, for the Lord God Omnipotent reigneth.</hi> In the yeare 1655. Chriſt and his Witneſſes are to take the powers of all the ten Kingdomes which Antichriſt had into their owne hands, and ſhall reigne; but yet Chriſt is not ſaid to reigne fully,<note place="margin">Chriſt not ſaid to reigne untill his reigne in and over his Church as well as over Nations.</note> untill An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt be quite removed out of the hearts of men, and the Church way of Chriſt clearly ſeene by all his ſervants, both by his Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Heaven, and other of his Saints, that ſo he may reigne, not onely upon the thrones of Nations, but likewiſe upon the hill of <hi>Sion</hi> his Church, and then Chriſt is ſaid to reigne truly; which he ſhall doe at this laſt terme 1700. Then ſhall the Lambe Chriſt be married unto his Church, and the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> built: Antichriſt being quite deſtroyed, and caſt, not onely out of the would, but out
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121084:37"/>of the hearts of men, and all that Antichriſtian darkneſſe and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance out of the mindes of men, that the way of Church-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline at that time ſhall be ſo plaine,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.8.</note> that wayfaring men, yea, though fools, ſhall not erre therein; and ſo much light, that all <hi>ſhall ſee the way of Church-diſcipline,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.7.</note> 
                  <hi>which way the uncleane is not to paſſe over, but it ſhall be for thoſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">At even time it ſhall be light, which is meant of this yeare 1700. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7. The Spouſe married to Chriſt by a Church-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</note> even for thoſe that are holy, which doe not pollute nor defile, and not for the uncleane. At which time all the people of God ſeeing the Church way of Chriſt ſo plaine, are ſaid <hi>to make themſelves ready and prepared to be married to Chriſt,</hi> not but that they were married to him before in a ſpirituall way by faith and love; Elſe how could they have this title of Bride or Wife? But to be married to him, is in an outward way by a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne <hi>League and Covenant</hi> in the ſight of all the world and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons round about them, which is called the building of that new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and holy City,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2, 10.</note> which is ſaid <hi>to come downe from Heaven.</hi> By Heaven is meant the place of judicature, where Chriſt and his Witneſſes ſit; from this high place or Heaven the Church and Spouſe of Chriſt, who is that new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> or holy City, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with liberty and leave from Chriſt and his Witneſſes, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a true Church-way, and to ſet up ſuch a Government in all the Churches of the Saints,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.22.</note> whereby the Lord Jeſus may be <hi>Mount</hi> Sion, <hi>and in his new</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>before his anciemts gloriouſly:</hi> The Lord Jeſus who is the Tree of Life,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.2.</note> who is in the midſt of his Church, is ſaid <hi>to yeeld twelve manner of fruits, twelve ſorts of fruits,</hi> after the twelve Tribes of the Children of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> That is, in him is all kindes of ſpirituall meats, to feed and nouriſh all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his Saints, though their wants be divers and many; <hi>And this Tree yeelds his fruit every moneth</hi> in the yeare. The holy Ghoſt ſecretly hinting to thoſe Churches that ſhall live in thoſe thouſand yeares, that he would have them to eat of that Tree of Life but once a moneth. Now by Tree of life is ſet forth to us the Lord Chriſt in that great Ordinance of the Lords Supper, who doth fully communicate himſelf to his Saints by that Ordinance. In other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances there is but a communication of Chriſt by parcels; but in this, of whole Chriſt, and a participation of all ſpirituall gifts and graces: and therefore the Lord Jeſus the Tree of life is ſaid to yeeld his fruit but once a moneth; therefore the Saints are not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121084:37"/>to take fruit from this Tree, but as it yeelds it, not to pluck the Tree before the fruits be ripe: and it is likely this will be the cuſtome of all the Churches in the thouſand yeares reigne.</p>
               <p>Though the Churches in the primitive times did receive it every ſeventh day, becauſe they were then in their infancy, and child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and ſo the Lord Jeſus had need to be as a Nurſe with his Breaſts full of Milke to nouriſh his young ones every day as it were: But when the Church ſhall be growne up to the age and ſtature of a man, and ſo to be fed with meat and not with milke, then Chriſt will be a Tree of life in his Church, yeelding meat and fruits for ſtrong men every moneth; for his Saints at that time are foretold by the holy Ghoſt, <hi>to be ancient men,</hi> ancient Chriſtians;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.23.</note> ſuch that are growne up towards the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.13.</note> before whom he is ſaid to reign in Mount <hi>Sion</hi> &amp; in <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> gloriouſly. This liberty to build this holy City, new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhal be to the Saints 1700. by the Witneſſes in the high place of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; therefore it is ſaid againe, <hi>That this holy City or new</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>commeth downe out of Heaven from God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>prepared as a Bride adorned for her Husband; the Spouſe of Christ had before her inward cloathing all of wrought gold, ſtanding on the right hand of the King in gold of Ophir;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.9.13.</note> called gold tryed in the fire, which made her ſpiritually rich and beautifull in her ſoule, in the eyes of her Lord and Husband Chriſt. But this is not ſufficient, ſhee muſt alſo have an outward raiment to make her beautifull without, both in the eyes of her Lord that looks upon her, and the men of this world; therefore it is ſaid, <hi>that ſhee ſhall be brought to the King in a raiment of needle-worke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.8.</note> 
                  <hi>curiouſly wrought and imbroidered, even in fine linen, clean &amp; white, which is the righteouſneſſe of the Saints:</hi> That which none hath right unto, or ought to meddle with but Saints,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.8.</note> it being the Government and Diſcipline which Chriſt is to ſet up and exerciſe in his owne Houſe and Temple over his Saints and people, and this fine linen was granted to her by Chriſt and his Witneſſes, and it was alſo granted to the ſoules un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Altar, which ſaw themſelves ſlaine for the teſtimony which they held, that they ſhould have white robes given them by Chriſt and his Witneſſes, when the fifth Seal was opened, which was when the fifth Viall was pouring forth, betwixt 1639. and 1655. but not fully to all the Saints untill the end of the ſeven Vials 1700.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.8.</note> And the holy Ghoſt gives the reaſon why no man, that is (not many) <hi>ſhall not be able to enter into the Temple, becauſe the Temple was filled with ſmoak from the glory of the Lord, and from his power.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:121084:38"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>By ſmoake</hi> is noted Gods preſence, Gods preſence in his Houſe and Temple is ſo glorious and ſo holy, that very few ſhall be able to endure it, his Government in his Houſe will be too ſtrict for looſe and formall ſpirits.</p>
               <p>By ſmoak is likewiſe noted darkneſſe, the way of Chriſts Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in and over all the Churches of the Saints, is for the preſent hard to be found out, it lyes deep, and is, as it were, hid in the inmoſt bowels of holy writ, not open in the letter of the Scripture, but wrapped up in the ſpirituall ſenſe thereof. And Antichriſt hath by his Antichriſtian ayre which he brought with him into the world, out of that bottomleſſe pit, ſo darkned the underſtanding of men, yea, of many of the deare Saints of God, that they cannot ſee Chriſts way in his Houſe and Temple.</p>
               <p>Again, Antichriſt having taken &amp; kept this Church power from the Saints 1260. years, and therefore they are, as it were, quite ignorant of this Diſcipline and Government (as well they may) therefore not able to enter into the Temple, but this Church power ſhall be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto the Saints again by Chriſt and his Witneſſes the year 1700.</p>
               <p>The Church being thus adorned with pure gold in her inward man, and with a broidered garment and fine linen upon her out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, and that by authority from Chriſts civill Magiſtrates in the place of Judicature,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.10, 11</note> is ſaid <hi>to deſcend out of Heaven from God, have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the glory of God, and her light was like unto a ſtone moſt precious, even like unto a Jaſper ſtone,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 3.</note> 
                  <hi>clear as Christall.</hi> And at this time the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of God ſhall be with men, even with the Saints and people, <hi>and he will dwell with them, and they ſhall be his people, and God himſelfe ſhall be with them and be their God,</hi> verſe 3. <hi>And God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes; and there ſhall be no more death, nor ſorrow, nor cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, neither ſhall there be any more paine.</hi> All thoſe teares, or death, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row or paine, which came by the oppreſſour, ſhall be taken away; <hi>for,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 4.</note> ſaith he, <hi>the former things are paſt away, all oppreſſion and tyranny of the enemy, and he that ſits upon the Throne will make all things new, new Heaven and new Earth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 5.</note> new Government in the Church, and a new Government in the State: In this new <hi>Jeruſalem ſhall be no Temple, nor need of the Sunne or Moone to ſhine in it:</hi> That is, the Church and people of God ſhall have no need of outward glory to make them beautifull in the eyes of Nations, <hi>but God and the Lambe ſhall have their ſpirituall Throne there,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>and be their light and glory, and his ſervants ſhall ſerve him, and ſhall ſee his face,</hi> that is the brightneſſe of his glory
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121084:38"/>
                  <hi>and his Name ſhall be in their fore-heads.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.4.</note> The power of Chriſt in his Church ſhalbe as viſible upon them, &amp; ſeen to belong to them at that day, as though it were written in their fore-heads. <hi>And in this City ſhall be a pure River of life, cleare as Chrystall:</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Verſe 1.</note> all pure Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of worſhip, which proceed from the Throne of God and the Lambe (who ſits in the midſt of his Church) and on both ſides of thoſe pure Ordinances is Chriſt, the Tree of life, communicating himſelfe to his Saints. Thus ſhall this holy City and new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> be built by authority from Chriſt and his Witneſſes in the yeare of Chriſt 1700. which ſhall be that great worke of the Witneſſes that ſame yeare throghout all their Dominions,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.8. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8, 9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9, 10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.23. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> which ſhall <hi>be from ſea to ſea, from the River even to the ends of the Earth,</hi> after they have kept ſilence in Heaven halfe an houre. At this time will God make good all his promiſes made unto Chriſt and his Saints concerning their reigning over the Nations, and upon the hill of him in his new <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> The two Governments of Chriſt, the one over the Nations, and another over his new <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> Chriſt reignes <hi>1000.</hi> yeares; Satan and wicked men bound all that ſame time, afterwards looſed and utterly destroyed; The Saints reigning three Termes.</head>
               <p>CHriſt and his Witneſſes having taken all power into their hands both Civill and Eccleſiaſticall, and being to reigne over the Nations, and upon Mount <hi>Zion</hi> and in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they muſt have two Governments ſet up to rule them by, one to rule the Nations, another to rule upon Mount <hi>Zion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That whereby Chriſt and his Saints is to reign and rule the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by, is juſt and righteous Lawes.<note place="margin">Chriſts go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.2.3.4. <hi>Verſe</hi> 7. <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.15.</note> 
                  <hi>A King ſhall reigne in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and Princes ſhall decree justice, he ſhall judge thy people with righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and the poore with judgement; the mountaines ſhall bring peace to the people, and the little hils by righteouſneſſe; he ſhall judge the poore of the people, he ſhall ſave the children of the needy, and ſhall breake in pieces the oppreſſour, and in his dayes ſhall the righteous flouriſh, and abundance of peace ſo long as the Moone endureth: at that time will I cauſe the Branch of righteouſneſſe to grow up to</hi> David, <hi>and he ſhall execute judgement and righteouſneſſe in the Land, juſtice and judgement ſhall be the habitation of his Throne, mercy and truth ſhall goe before thy face;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.14. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.5.</note> 
                  <hi>a King ſhall reigne and proſper who ſhall execute judgement in the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:121084:39"/>
               <p>Secondly, Chriſt will not only give them juſt and righteous Laws, but he will alſo give them his Goſpel,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6. <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.16.</note> 
                  <hi>which ſhalbe preached to all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; they ſhal come up to</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>to worſhip, &amp; keep the feaſt of Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacles.</hi> They ſhall ſubmit to his power ſo farre as to have the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel preached to the people of the Nations:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.2.</note> Which Goſpel is called <hi>the leaves of that Tree of life,</hi> which is to heale the Nations of their deadly wounds and diſeaſes, <hi>that they may doe the Commandements of God, and have right to the Tree of life, and ſo enter in through the Gate in-that holy City,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.17.</note> 
                  <hi>new Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Government by which Chriſt will rule in the world,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.35.</note> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The new Earth,</hi> which God promiſed to make (the old earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſſed away, even that old Government of oppreſſions and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty which the five Beaſts ſet up,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1.</note> being now diſſolved by Chriſt and his Witneſſes; Chriſt ſet up a new Government to governe the men of the earth by, called <hi>The new Earth,</hi> luſt and righteous Lawes, and his Goſpell,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6.</note> to be preached unto all Nations.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Government which Chriſt is to ſet up in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of his Saints and new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is a more ſtricter government then the former:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.15.16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1.</note> 
                  <hi>He ſhall ſit upon the throne of his glory in his Church and Temple, with a meaſuring line and golden reed, to meaſure</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>that holy City, to ſee that the length and bredth and hight of it be equall;</hi> the higheſt Officer, and the meaneſt Member of the Church muſt be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall in point of power: <hi>and with this rod or golden reed he is to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Temple of God, and the Altar, and them that worſhip therein; but the outward Court muſt not be meaſured.</hi> They that come into the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Court; that is, they that come to the preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, meaſure not them, for it is given to all the Nations of the world to be <hi>as leaves of the Tree of life</hi> to cure them therewith; but the ſtones of the Temple and Altar, and they that worſhip therein, muſt be meaſured.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Chriſt will meaſure all the ſtones which this holy City, new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is to be built withall, none is to be admitted <hi>but preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.18.</note> 
                  <hi>even of Jaſper, godly men and women, and the city is to be all of pure gold, like unto clcere glaſſe.</hi> None are to enter into a Church-league and Covenant, to be a ſtone of this new Jernſalem, but ſuch as have their cloathing of wrought gold,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.13.</note> befitting the Spouſe of Chriſt and Queen of Heaven, thoſe graees of Gods Spirit which are as gold tryed in the fire,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.18.</note> like unto cleare glaſſe, without ſpot or defilement, which are ſo, I ſay, in the judgement of Charity, for ſo muſt the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121084:39"/>Saints judge, if one be without ſpot, not defilling by any outward ſin, as to worke abomination, or make a lye, he is to be admitted, the Saints is to believe that ſuch a one is a precious ſtone, and pure gold, in the judgement of charity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Temple muſt not only be meaſured, that is, godly men and women which are as lively ſtones, and ſpirituall,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2.5. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.13.</note> to build this ſpirituall Temple, but <hi>the Altar muſt be meaſured,</hi> all ordinances and inſtruments, with which the Saints are to worſhip, are to be meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; nothing is to be admitted as an Ordinance of worſhip, but what is of divine inſtitution, which will agree with the touch-ſtone of the Word, and ballance of the Sanctuary: Not any of that <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> traſh of mens inventions and humane traditions, with which the Whore of <hi>Rome</hi> mixed her cup,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.26, 27.</note> 
                  <hi>but the Altar muſt be cleanſed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven daies, ſeven times,</hi> as gold or ſilver, and then the Lord will accept of our offerings, <hi>Theſe are the Ordinances of the Altar of Chriſt within his Temple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. They that worſhip in the Temple muſt be meaſured, Chriſt ſits upon the throne of his Church in the Temple, and all that come in after it is built, to worſhip, ſhall be meaſured, if they doe not agree with the golden reede of divine truth, no admittance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Temple; nay, after they be admitted, if they walke not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of the Goſpell, after the third admonition,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17.</note> they are to be caſt out of his houſe:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</note> As none ſhall enter into his houſe that defiles, ſo nothing is admitted to ſtay there, for he would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file all the reſt. <hi>A little leaven leaveneth the whole lump;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6.</note> therefore he muſt be cut off by the ſword of Chriſt that goeth out of his mouth. This is that government and diſcipline which Chriſt will ſet up in his Temple and holy City,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.16.</note> and exerciſe in all the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of his Saints all the 1000. yeares, and to the end of the world: <hi>And theſe are the lawes, ordinances, and forms, and going out thereof, and commings in thereof, this is the law of the houſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.12.</note> 
                  <hi>upon the top of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</hi> which is called that new Heaven which he will make,<note place="margin">A new Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> that old Heaven being paſſed away; and there was found no more ſea, no more of that Romiſh doctrine or humane traditions which that Antichriſtian Whore brought into the world with her; but that Roman Beaſt, and Babyloniſh Whore, with all her abominations, is now to be removed out of the way, which ſhe ſet up in the Temple and Heaven; and now the Lord ſets up pure ordinances of worſhip
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121084:40"/>in all the Churches of the Saints, which he calls the new Heaven, which new heaven and earth ſhall ever continue,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.3, 4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.22.</note> not only for 1000. yeares, in which Chriſt and his Saints ſhall raigne, Satan be bound, and wicked men ſhut up as priſoners in a pit, and lye civilly ſlaine, but even to the worlds end; and then ſhall that be fulfilled, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 16.16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21. <hi>Thou ſhalt alſo ſuck the milke of, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the Lord Jeſus is to raigne over the Nations of the world and Churches of his Saints, 1000. yeares, which 1000. yeares begins when Antichriſt is quite deſtroyed, which will be 1700. yeares, and continue unto 2700. in which time Satan is ſaid to be bound and ſhut up,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.3.</note> and ſealed in that bottomleſſe pit: Not ſo ſhut up, but he ſhall ſtill tempt and intice the men of the world, yea, and Saints too, to ſin; but this, he ſhall be bound from tempting men to civill war againſt one another,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mic.</hi> 4.3.</note> all that 1000. years, <hi>and therefore they are ſaid, not to learne war any more,</hi> that is, not all that 1000. yeares; and wicked men ſhall be civilly ſlain and laid as dead men, and not to live untill that 1000. years be ended,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5.</note> and ſhut up as priſoners in a pit; not but that they ſhall have as much liberty as the Saints in an outward way, to trade and to have commerce in the world, but they ſhall have all civill power taken out of their hands, and ſo lie as dead men, and uſeleſſe men in the State or Kingdome where they live, and be in that reſpect as priſoners gathered into a pit, and ſhut up in priſon.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.22.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But after this thouſand yeares is ended, then Satan ſhall be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in the yeare 2700. and the reſt of the wicked,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.22.</note> which were civilly dead, ſhall live, and the priſoners which were ſhut up, ſhall be viſited; that is, let forth out of their priſon, and the Devil ſhall go out to deceive the Nations of the earth, by ſtirring up wicked men to make civill war with the Saints; and the wicked of the earth ſhall be ſuffered by God to take up armes againſt his people, and ſo are ſaid to be let out of priſon, for it is a priſon to wicked men and the Devill,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5.</note> to be kept from warring againſt the people of God. And likewiſe are ſaid to live when the 1000. yeeres are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that is, civilly, they now having taken up Armes, have civill power in their hands,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.1.</note> and ſo live, <hi>And they ſhall gather together into a great Army horſes and horſemen, all of them cloathed with all ſorts of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, even a great company; all of them handling the ſword, the number of whom is as the ſand of the ſea,</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Magog. <hi>The chiefe Princes of</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:121084:40"/>Meſhech <hi>and</hi> Tubal, <hi>Captaines of this great Army, ſhall goe upon the breadth of the earth, and compaſſe the Campe of the Saints, and the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved City.</hi> But God will deſtroy them with a mighty deſtruction.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, he will call for <hi>a ſword againſt him throughout all his Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</hi> or powers of States, all being in the hands of him and his Saints at the ſame time throughout the world.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38.21.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, God will turne the ſword of the enemy againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>every mans ſword ſhall be againſt his brother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>God will ſend his peſtilence into their army,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 23.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.2, 4.9.12. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.23.</note> 
                  <hi>and raigne upon them great haile-ſtones, fire and brinstone, and but the ſixt part of them ſhall returne back, and the reſt ſhall fall upon the Mountaine of Iſrael, and the people of God ſhall be ſeven moneths burying the dead, and ſeven yeares burning their weapons; Thus will the Lord magnifie and ſanctifie his great Name in the fight of the Heathen, and in the eyes of many Nations, and they ſhall know that he is the Lord, and they ſhall know that the people of Iſrael went into captivity, for their iniquity and for their ſin; Therefore God hid his face from them, and gave them all into the hands of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and the houſe of Iſrael ſhall know that the Lord is their God, from that day forwards; neither will he hide his face from them any more, becauſe he hath poured his Spirit upon them;</hi> And thus ſhall God deſtroy this great army of <hi>Gog</hi> &amp; <hi>Magog, &amp; the Devil that deceived them ſhall be caſt into a lake of fire burning with brimſtone,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev</hi> 20.10.</note> 
                  <hi>where the Beaſt and falſe prophets are, and ſhall be tormented day and night, for ever and ever.</hi> And then the Saints of God, and Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall reigne in peace and quiet, never to be moleſted by the Devill and wicked men, in a way of civill war more, and ſhall reigne to the end of the world; but when that end of the world ſhall be, is not knowne Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our gave foure ſignes of his comming to judge Antichriſt, but of that laſt judgement of quick and dead, <hi>when Chriſt ſhall deliver up the Kingdome to his Father, and God to be all in all,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. &amp; 28. <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.32.</note> 
                  <hi>of this day and houre knowes no man, no not the Angels in Heaven, neither the Son, but the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Onely he hath hid this time and ſeaſon in his owne heart and breaſt, and it is not for us to ſearch into it, or to meddle with it; It may be hundreds or thouſands of yeares after this yeare, 2700. when <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>But this is noted in the Scripture of truth, that the Saints ſhall reigne for three periods, <hi>they ſhall take and poſſeſſe the Kingdom for ever even for ever and ever.</hi> Ever is a terme of time;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.8.</note> the firſt ever begins
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121084:41"/>1655. when the Beaſt, and the falſe prophet, and their Armies ſhall be deſtroyed, and the Saints take poſſeſſion of the Kingdome to the yeare 1700. unto which time the ſeventh Viall ſhalbe pouring upon that Antichriſtian aire, and ſo caſt out of the world, as out of the grave, as an abominable branch.</p>
               <p>Second Ever is from the yeare 1700. to the yeare 2700. all that 1000. yeares reigne of Chriſt and his Saints, wherein Satan is to be bound, and the wicked civilly ſlaine and lye dead; at the end of which terme they ſhall aſſay to take the power out of the hands of the Saints, but ſhall not be able. This is the ſecond terme of time, or ever, to which the Saints ſhall raigne.</p>
               <p>The third Ever is from the yeare of Chriſt 2700. to the end of the world, when Jeſus Chriſt ſhall come to judge the quick and dead, and deliver up the Kingdome to his Father, and God be all in all.</p>
               <p>Then alſo who knows whether the Lord will fulfill all theſe things in a literall and naturall way, at his laſt and perſonall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to judgment, as he hath fulfilled them in a ſpirituall and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall ſenſe, as hath been ſhewed in this diſcourſe, ſo that the ſun ſhalbe darkened, and the moon be turned into blood, the ſtars fall from Heaven, Heaven and Earth to be rolled together as a ſcroll, and paſſe away, and their place be no more found, and the ſea not only to roare, but there to be no more ſea; and a new Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and a new Earth to be made by the almighty power of God, which ſhalbe as a great new City for the ſervants of God to dwell in, and to behold his face, and ſee his glory, which City will have no need of the light of a naturall ſun or moone, for the Lord God and the Lambe will be the light and glory thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
